<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Loves companion, or, A short treatise of the nature, necessity, and advantages of moderation being the substance of two sermons preached at Ousburne, By J. H. M.A. and minsiter of Ousburne.</title>
            <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832669</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832669</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2148:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Loves companion, or, A short treatise of the nature, necessity, and advantages of moderation being the substance of two sermons preached at Ousburne, By J. H. M.A. and minsiter of Ousburne.</title>
                  <author>Hunter, Josiah, minister in York.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Francis Leach,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The dedication is signed: Josiah Hunter.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Moderation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Loves Companion, OR, A SHORT TREATISE Of the Nature, Neceſsity, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of MODERATION, Being the ſubſtance of two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preached at <hi>Ouſburne,</hi> by <hi>J. H.</hi> M. A. and Miniſter of <hi>Ouſburne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Be not righteous over-much, neither make thy ſelf over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, why ſhouldeſt thou destroy thy ſelf?</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>7. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ariſtot. lib. 2. Ethic. capit. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Leach,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:2"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull THOMAS DICKINSON <abbr>Eſq</abbr>, and a worthy Member of the Honourable Houſe of Parliament</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the obſervation of a learned man out of <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> that Chriſt is always crucified between two Theeves, that is, Truth ſuffers between two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream Errors: and I have obſerved, that the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man is ever cruſhed between two extream par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, who becauſe he would have them both friends, is looked upon by both as an Enemy. Yet methinks, now, if ever, a Treatiſe of Moderation ſhould be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, after we have had ſuch ſore and ſure experience of the evils that ariſe from its contrary. I know it would have been to as little purpoſe, to have preſented to publike view a ſubject of this nature, in the times of our buſie wars, as it is to give advice to a man in the heat, and height of his paſſion: but now that things af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo many years of confuſion, are grown more calm and compoſed; I hope likewiſe, that mens ſpirits are accordingly tempered; eſpecially having proved by trial, that becauſe they would ſuffer nothing before, they are now forced almoſt to ſuffer every thing; this is a ſharp remedy, but Pride, Uncharitableneſs, and Hypocriſie, are ſore diſeaſes; if the Lord ſhall hereby cure us of theſe ſins, and afterwards reſtore, and ſettle us, we ſhall have cauſe to acknowledge his dealing with us, not only juſt, but mercifull.</p>
            <p>One great enemy unto moderation, are deep and dangerous engagements unto a party, which make men
<pb facs="tcp:37143:3"/>
of that deſperate humour, as to reſolve according to the Proverb, That becauſe they have gone over Shooes, they will over Boots too. There is but one thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to make a wiſe man, that is, Conſideration; yet that Conſideration is twofold, either before or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fact; the former tends to prevent a miſchief be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it come, the latter to remove and heal it, when through inadvertency it is come; the former is better, yet the latter is good, if not out of ſeaſon; for as we ſay, Better late wiſe than never: But ſuch is the proud humour of deeply-engaged perſons, that they refuſe to put in practice the latter, becauſe they would not be thought to have neglected the former; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve rather to continue fools even <hi>ad delirium &amp; inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam,</hi> than they will be thought, once not to have been ſo wiſe as they might have been. Theſe men are of the Forlorne hope, and their Word is, Go forward, but their forwardneſs is frowardneſs, and if not ſeaſonably repreſſed by Authority, will precipitate themſelves and others into deſtruction. I confeſs that to backſlide in matters of Religion is both baſe and ſinfull; but if a man hath over-ſhot himſelf, and gone too far, it is both his wiſdom and ſafety in time to look back. God forbid, that any who profeſſeth himſelf to be an <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,</hi> ſhould think of returning back to <hi>Aegypt;</hi> no, fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all cringing, and croſſing, and bowing, with ſuch like dregs of refined Popery, that they may never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn again, till his Holineſſe by the help of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Son reduce the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is my Prayer unfeignedly. But in things that tend to the order and well-being of the Church, which are at preſent, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the other, utterly demoliſhed, there is no doubt but Authority will give us leave to look back to the Conſtitutions of the Primitive Church, and the Conſtitutions of our own Church formerly (ſo far forrh as agreeing with them, and not repugnant to the Scriptures) except we ſhould depend upon an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Revelation for our direction.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:37143:3"/>A ſecond enemy unto Moderation is Hypocriſie, and ſelf-endedneſs, theſe make men that they do not ſo much deſire publike ſettlement, as private ſafety, and cauſeth them altogether to hold off from engaging themſelves to take up the quarrels of the Church, leſt if their endeavours ſhould prove unſucceſsfull, they might ſuffer by it. Such as theſe may be obſerved to ſtand not <hi>in medio,</hi> but <hi>in bivio,</hi> expecting the event, that they may apply themſelves accordingly.<note place="margin">Pelago ſe non ita commiſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſſe, qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quando liberet pedem referre poſſet, Melch. Adam in Vit. Bez.</note> As King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>Navarre</hi> told <hi>Beza,</hi> who urged him to ſhew himſelf in the quarrel of the Proteſtants Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that he would keep upon the ſhore, and not launch too ar out into the deep; but ſo that if a ſtorm ſhould ariſe, he might ſoon get to land again: A Leſſon that, it ſeems, <hi>Baldwin,</hi> a man in great eſteem among the <hi>French,</hi> but a very <hi>Ecebolus</hi> in Religion, taught him. It was once the Speech of a deep Politician, that it was good to follow the truth, but not too near at the heels, leſt it ſhould daſh out his brains: But if all men were of this mind, when would the quarrels of our Church be taken up? certainly not till the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if out Church ſhould continue ſo long.</p>
            <p>A third Enemy unto Moderation is Pride and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity, I joyn them both together, becauſe they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom goe aſunder: A man cannot be moderate, who is not ſetled in his judgement, and humble in his appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: now Pride makes a man ſtiff, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance is neceſſary; popularity makes him baſe in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion, where fixedneſs of reſolution is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, there are ſome that live by quarrels and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, who are of all others the greateſt Enemies unto Moderation. Theſe are of his mind, that bade when the ſword was drawn, throw the Scabbard to the Devil. We read in <hi>Plutarch</hi> of one <hi>Demades,</hi> by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a maker of Coffins, that was baniſhed out of the City of <hi>Athens,</hi> for wiſhing that he might have good trading; that Wiſe State truly interpreting the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb facs="tcp:37143:4"/>
of his wiſh; as deſiring ſome Epidemical diſeaſe, his private profit being inconſiſtent with the publike flouriſhing of the Commonwealth: ſo thoſe people, who are undone, and cannot live but by undoing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, certainly wiſh no good to our Church or Nation; but muſt needs be State Barretours, to keep the ſore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes raw between Magiſtrates and Miniſters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Governours and their people.</p>
            <p>Sir, beſides all theſe, I have obſerved two great evils under the Sun, and they are theſe. That if a man be zealous he ſhall preſently be accounted immoderate by prophane perſons, and if he be moderate, he ſhall be thought to be lukewarm by hot profeſſors: So that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween prophaneſs and indiſcretion, it is almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for a man to maintain his reputation; for thoſe which condemn zeal (that keeps it ſelf within its own circuit) under the pretence of immoderation, they are ſcarce worth the anſwering: <hi>Ahab</hi> accuſed <hi>Elijah</hi> for the troubler of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Tertullus</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> for a peſtilent fellow, and a mover of ſedition, and <hi>Michol</hi> deſpiſed <hi>David</hi> as a vain perſon, when in his zeal he danced before the Ark; yet the Holy Ghoſt commends all theſe for their zeal; but no where condemns them of Immoderation. For ſuch as condemn Moderation for lukewarmneſſe, if they be obſerved in the general courſe of their lives to be conſcientious, they are to be pitied &amp; directed; but if they be carnal &amp; Time-ſerving Profeſſors, they are to be ſharply dealt with, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected, as thoſe whom we may juſtly ſuſpect for Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, and the driving on ſome privare deſign. I will only adde this, that of all men, they who plead for a Toleration, have the leaſt reaſon to accuſe moderate perſons of lukewarmneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> I might have added much more to what I have ſaid concerning the Enemies of Moderation. Give me leave to ſay a little in vindication of men of mine own function, the Prieſts (as the Sectaries &amp; Star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazers call them) who lie under the <hi>Odium</hi> of Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb facs="tcp:37143:4"/>
I do freely confeſſe, that if the Lot ſhould be caſt, I fear many of our Tribe would be taken; yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for them I think, I may ſafely ſay this, that many ſpeak Againſt them, for ſpeaking but that, which they themſelves think. But for others, who doth not ſee, that therefore they are accounted immoderate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do zealouſly declare againſt the Hereſies and Corruptions of the times, and the giving of Credence to the predictions of every vain Sooth-ſayer and Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger, falſly ſo called? Again, I may ſubjoyn this, that many Miniſters are more ſtrict than otherwiſe they would be, becauſe they ſee, that people are Generally more looſe, not only in their practice, but their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, than they have been; herein imitating a carefull Father, who holds a more ſtrict hand over his child, than otherwiſe he would, becauſe he ſees that his natural inclination, together with the temptations of evil company, provoke him to break out into ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, as are not only ſin in him, but ſhame to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Thirdly, therefore it may be, ſome Miniſters are the more ſtiff, becauſe they know, when they come to a debate, they muſt be forced to abate ſomething, and cannot with ſafety abate too much; as a Chapman will ask full as much, as his commodity is worth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe elſe he knows, that he ſhall be bidden leſs than it is worth; all the danger is, that if a man ask too much, perhaps he ſhall be bidden nothing at all. Laſtly, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple expect zeal from Miniſters, though they care not for it themſelves; as many that care not ſo much for prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, as to come conſtantly once on a Lords-day, who yet would be ready to Article againſt their Miniſter, if he did not preach twice. That which <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, <hi>Nunquam periclitatur Religio, niſi inter Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimos;</hi> the Vulgar are readie enough to take up as a Maxim, or an Oracle. It is obſerved, when Chriſt was crucified, <hi>Pilate</hi> the Civil Magiſtrate abſolved him, <hi>Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> the High Prieſt condemned him, <hi>Judas,</hi> his own diſciple, betrayed him: people are willing to waſh
<pb facs="tcp:37143:5"/>
their hands, as <hi>Pilate</hi> did, and think they have done all well enough, if they can with any colour lay the blame at the Miniſters door. Sure it is, cold Miniſters make bold ſinners; and all the blame will be laid upon the unfaithfull Miniſtry, that ſhould have been burning and ſhining lights, if Atheiſm or Hereſie grow to an height.</p>
            <p>Sir, I know you bear honourable reſpects, out of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to all conſcientious Miniſters, however tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and maligned by ſome Apoſtatical perſons. And this (ſet aſide my private engagement, the publike re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital whereof would not make others more to wonder, than your ſelf to bluſh) hath induced me to dedicate this Sermon to you, as a teſtimony of that honor which I bear to you, and cannot otherwiſe to the world ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe. It was intended for you by the unworthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, when the other Sermon (concerning <hi>Mutual Love</hi>) was put forth, if the Printers ſlackneſſe had not prevented, and I am ſure, I have no reaſon to alter my intentions. For my ſelf, I wiſh, that the Sermon were but in any reſpect worthy of your patronage, as you are in every reſpect worthy of its dedication. For you, I wiſh, that you may indeed ſhow, that you patronize it by practiſing it. And that your Zeal may not burn up your Moderation; nor your Moderation choak your Zeal, is the prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>October 25th 1656.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips humbly devoted,</hi> Joſiah Hunter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:5"/>
            <head>To the Moderate Reader.</head>
            <p>THat I am not ambitious of being ſeen in Print, this is no ſmall Argument, that I have ſuffered this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon (though ready for the Preſs) to lie beſide me theſe ſeven moneths, when I know, it was expected by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, to be made publike every week: That which hath been a great incouragement, now at laſt, to expoſe it, is not hope of gain or credit, but the preſent calmneſs and ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the times, wherein a Sermon of Moderation ſhall not be ſo bold to look out, but it ſhall be as acceptably taken in. When one preſented a Treatiſe of Iuſtice to <hi>Antigonus</hi> (at that very time beſieging a City) he told him, that he came out of ſeaſon; And it was the ſaying of a King, when a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Happineſs was offered to him, that he was not at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; And perhaps if this Treatiſe ſhould have been preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to publike view, whilſt we were in the heat of our civil wars, it might have been thought to have come out of ſeaſon, and few or none would have been at leiſure to read it: But now, after ſuch a bleſſed ceſſation of war, inſomuch that Councels of War are turned into Councels of State, I hope this ſubject will come in ſeaſon, and even the Souldier will have leiſure enough to read it.</p>
            <p>I know it is a very nice and tickle point, which whoſoever undertakes to handle, it will be expected from him, that he ſhould find out the <hi>maximum quod ſic,</hi> and the <hi>minimum quod non:</hi> and that he ſhould be like thoſe men of <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> who could ſling ſtones at an hair-breadth, and not miſs, <hi>Jud. 20.16. Antoninus Pius,</hi> for his deſire to ſearch to the
<pb facs="tcp:37143:6"/>
leaſt differences, was called (in a by word) <hi>Cumini Sector,</hi> a Carver of Cummine ſeed. But a man cannot be too exact in a ſubject of this Nature, in dividing (if it were poſſible) to an hairs breadth between the two extreams of Moderation: wherein (I ſhould be moſt vainly conceited of my ſelf) if I did not ſuspect, that I had failed. Yet this I have to plead in way of Apologye for my ſelf, that it is a ſubject whereof few have written profeſſedly; None that ever I ſaw, except Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> in his Holy State, of whom I think it no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit to be a borrower, and ſo far as I remember, I have not concealed any thing that was borrowed.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why I entitle this Sermon <hi>(Loves Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)</hi> is, becauſe that Moderation is always a Concomitant of Love, and likewiſe becauſe I intended at firſt, that it ſhould have been printed with, and joyned to that Sermon of Mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Love. If there be any thing elſe which I have promiſed, and thou expecteſt, I ſhall (as God gives aſſiſtance, and this finds acceptance) endeavour, according to my poor abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to anſwer thine expectation; but for the preſent I have engaged my ſelf to adde unto theſe ſomething concerning the Enemies of Love and Moderation, the greateſt part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is at preſent ready. In the mean time, if thou receive any benefit by this, Bleſſe God, and pray for the unworthy Instrument, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine to ſerve thee in our Lord Jeſus,</hi> JOSIAH HUNTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37143:6"/>
            <head>Loves Companion.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Philipp: 4.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let your moderation be known unto all men: the Lord is at hand.<note place="margin">Text:</note>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two things, Beloved, which were never more needfull to be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed than now; and they are Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Zeal. Perhaps ſome may judge this at the firſt reading to be a ſtrange paradox, but it is a real truth; and if there be any thing ſtrange, it is in the times, into which we are fallen, that do at once require both a great meaſure of Zeal, &amp; a great deal of Moderation; for who doth not ſee, that in things of leſs concernment, mere notions &amp; ſpeculations, how hot we are? here therefore is need of Moderation. But on the other ſide, who ſees not, that in things of weighty importance, both for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of doctrine and practice, faith and love; how cold we are? here therefore is need of Zeal. How hot ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men are in defending an opinion, and yet cold in oppoſing an hereſie? how hot many men are in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a ceremonie, and yet lukewarm in the maintenance of things of greater concernment? and the truth is, I never knew the violent proſecution of ſpeculations and politicks, but it was ever accompanied with a cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and looſneſs in piety and practice. I ſhall make choice of another opportunitie to ſpeak concerning Zeal, for the preſent my ſubject ſhall be Moderation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:37143:7"/>And for the right underſtanding of theſe words, you muſt Conſider, that theſe <hi>Philippians,</hi> to whom the Apoſtle directs his Epiſtle, were in a ſuffering conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as appears out of 1 Phil. 27. <hi>Only let your conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation be, as becommeth the Goſpel of Chriſt, ſtanding fast in one ſpirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for the faith of the Goſpel; and in nothing terrified by your adverſaries, which is to them an evident token of perdition, but to you of ſalvation, and that of God; for unto you it is given on the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe in him, but alſo to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for his ſake, having the ſame conflict, which you ſaw in me, and now hear to be in me.</hi> Upon theſe ſuffering Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians therefore it is, that the Apoſtle layes this injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>Let your moderation be known unto all men;</hi> adding alſo a reaſon to enforce it, <hi>the Lord is at hand:</hi> how at hand? that is, either for your preſent ſuccour, as it is in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.1. <hi>God is our refuge and ſtrength: a very preſent help in trouble.</hi> Or he will come ſhortly to judgement, and put an end to all your ſufferings, and revenge all the wrongs offer'd to his people; as you have it, <hi>James</hi> 5.8. <hi>Be ye alſo patient, ſtabliſh your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh.</hi> So that though it be many years off in your account, yet it is not many dayes in Gods account, with whom <hi>one day is as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, and a thouſand years as one day,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let your moderation be known to all men.</hi> The Vulgar Intetpreter renders it <hi>Modeſtia veſtra,</hi> your Modeſtie; which though it be an effect of Moderation yet it is not moderation it ſelf; no more than bluſhing can properly be ſaid to be modeſtie, becauſe it is an effect of it; but as bluſhing proceeds ſometimes from modeſtie, ſo doth modeſtie from Moderation. In the Original it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, your equitie, or rather equabilitie, or equal carriage, being neither too much lifted up in wrath, clamor, or evil ſpeaking, becauſe of the ſins of your adverſaries; nor too much dejected and caſt down be cauſe of the oppreſſions &amp; ſufferings, which you ſuſtain from your adverſaries. Let this your moderation, or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37143:7"/>
equall carriage <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> be known, that is, let it be ſuch, that it may be manifeſt; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to all men; not only your friends, but your enemies; not only to the godly, and ſuch as are well-affected to you, but likewiſe to the wicked, and ſuch as are ill-affected to you. Hence I might give you the obſervation, That it is not enough, for a Chriſtian to have grace, but he muſt alſo in his converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manifeſt it, that it may be known to others, even all men. But that which I intend is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Chriſtians ought to carry themſelves ſo at all times, but eſpecially in ſuffering times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv.</note> 
               <hi>that their Moderation may be manifeſt to all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the improvement of this point, I will endeavour theſe three things, 1. To ſhew you what this Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is. 2. Why it is the duty of a Chriſtian to expreſs it. 3. Why eſpecially in ſuffering times. Firſt, What this Moderation is? to which I anſwer, firſt negatively, what it is not; where I remove three things. 1. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is not an halting between two opinions, when the thorow beleeving of one of them is neceſſary unto Salvation. <hi>Elijah</hi> ſaid unto the people, <hi>How long will you halt between two opinions? If the Lord be God, then follow him, but if</hi> Baal, <hi>follow him.</hi> 2 Kings 18.20. Such were they we read of 1 Zeph. 5. <hi>That worſhipped, and that ſware by the Lord, and that ſware by</hi> Malcham. This halting argueth at the beſt, great weakneſs and inſtability both of judgement and affection; if not a corrupt and rotten judgement and affection. Contrary to this halting is upright walking, which is ſo often and ſo much commended to us in Scripture. <hi>The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of the upright ſhall guide them.</hi> Prov. 11.3. <hi>As for the Upright he directeth his way,</hi> Prov. 21.29. <hi>And the way of the Lord is ſtrength to the upright,</hi> 10 Prov. 29. Though a man be weak, yet if he be upright, the way of the Lord ſhall be ſtrength to him, and his upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall guide him and direct him in the way. Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting therefore comes from Hypocriſie, at the leaſt, from unſettledneſs. We read in<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mr. Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in his Holy State.</note> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 27 12. of an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37143:8"/>
that lay towards the South-weſt, and towards the North-weſt. It is ſtrange that it could have part of two ſo oppoſite parts, North and South; ſure it muſt needs be very winding: Yet there are ſome mens Souls in ſuch intricate poſtures, that they lie towards the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and towards the Proteſtants; and among Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants there are many that lie towards Anabaptiſme, Judaiſme, Arminianiſme, &amp;c. ſuch as theſe we account not of a moderate judgement, but of an immoderate unſettledneſs; or indeed, the falſeneſs of their hearts is rather to be feared, than the meer fickleneſs of their judgements. <hi>Peter</hi> (and therefore no ſuch wonder of other men, though in theſe times eminent) was not altogether free from this halting between the Jews and Gentiles, and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood him to the face, and told him openly of his diſſimulation. 2 <hi>Gal.</hi> 11, 12, 13. Only obſerve what I ſay; I ſay that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is not an halting between two opinions, when the thorough beleeving of one of them is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary unto Salvation: Otherwiſe, if the thing be not neceſſary unto Salvation, it may be Wiſedom ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a moderate man, to ſuſpend his judgement in himſelf, at leaſt the declaration of his judgement un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others.</p>
            <p>The like alſo may be ſaid in matters of practice: he is not a moderate man, but a Newter, that holds off from both, when the Glory of God, and the good of the Church or State doth require him to engage himſelf on one ſide. <hi>Curſe ye</hi> Meroz <hi>(ſaid the Angel of the Lord) curſe ye bitterly the Inhabitants thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5 <hi>Jud.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the mighty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Whereas</hi> Zebulun <hi>and</hi> Naphtali <hi>are highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, becauſe they jeoparded their lives unto the death in the high places of the field.</hi> Such a one we account not a moderate man, but an immoderate lover of himſelf, and his own private intereſt, who ſtays in his Tent, when God calls him into the field; and cannot be drawn from the ſmoak of his own Chimney to quench
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37143:8"/>
a publike fire. This is baſeneſs of mind, as far below Moderation in the defect; as a proud and ambitious adventuring of a mans ſelf beyond his calling, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a call, is above it in the exceſs. He cannot be tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therefore for a man that exceeds the bounds of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, who being fully aſſured and convinced of the lawfullneſs in the general, and the preſent neceſſity in particular, doth freely engage himſelf, though it be to the hazard of his life, in the defence of the truth of the Goſpel, and the cauſe of God, againſt Papiſts, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians, Anabaptiſts, Atheiſts, and prophane perſons, or whomſoever elſe of that ſame coin or ſtamp.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, it is apparent, that upright Moderation differs from halting Neutrality in two things, in Sincetity, and in Settledneſs: the latter flows from the former; for therefore is a moderate man ſetled, becauſe he is ſincere; for Truth is uniform, and alwaies like to it ſelf. The Philoſopher ſaith of a juſt man, that he is like a Dye, which is every way even and like it ſelf, turn it how you will, it falls upon an equall botttome: the like might be ſaid of an upright man. But the Newter is like an unballaſted ſhip, that toples up and down in the Sea, and bends ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to one Shoar, ſometimes to another, but Lands no where not but that the Ground is good to land on, but he is not reſolved yet, on which ſide he had beſt to land: and therefore he ſails between both, and to keep both in fair hopes, he ſalutes them ſometimes on one ſide, ſometimes on the other, but he will Land on neither, till he ſee he can make his own advantage. The moderate man is not afraid or unwilling to intereſt himſelf in the neceſſary quarrels of the Church; the Newter, like a prophane Atheiſt, will engage himſelf on neither, but ſtands by and laughs at the diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of both parties, and cares not much on whoſe ſide the Victory fall, ſo it do but end in peace. He much weighs not whether Truth get the better of Error in this quarrel, ſo that Peace do but get the better of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37143:9"/>
Diſſention, that he may lead a quiet, for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lead a godly life or no, he doth but little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Moderation is not a Lukewarmneſs in thoſe things, wherein Gods glory is concerned; here it is a true Rule,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> loc. ſupr. cit. Turpe eſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ardeuter perverſa aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, nos pro veritate frigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diores inveniri. <hi>Ruſt. Diac. lib.</hi> adverſus <hi>Acephalos</hi> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Dr. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fere</hi> in his Path-way to perfection.</note> 
               <hi>Non amat qui non zelat,</hi> and they that are thus lukewarm here, ſhall be too hot hereafter in that Oven, wherein Dough-baked Cakes ſhall be burnt. And a great ſhame it is for us to be cold in defending the Truth, when our Adverſaries are ſo hot in oppoſing it. Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit was ſtirred in him, when he ſaw the whole City given to Idolatry, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.16. How earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt alſo was our Saviour, when he drove the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple? then his Diſciples remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred that it was written, <hi>The zeal of thine Houſe hath eaten me up, John</hi> 2.15, 17. was not <hi>Nehemiah</hi> zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous when he contended with the Rulers, and ſaid, <hi>Why is the Houſe of God forſaken? and in thoſe daies</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſaw men working, and bearing all manner of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens on the Sabbath day, ſo I teſtified againſt them, and I contended with the Nobles of</hi> Judah, <hi>and ſaid unto them, what evill thing is this, that ye do, and prophane the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath? And when divers Merchants came and brought ware to ſell on the Sabbath day, I teſtified againſt them, and ſaid unto them, why lodge you al out the Wall? If you do ſo again, I will lay hands on you. In thoſe daies alſo</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I ſaw</hi> Jews, <hi>that had maried wives of</hi> Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dod, Ammon <hi>and</hi> Moab; <hi>and their Children ſpake half in the Speech of</hi> Aſhdod, <hi>and could not ſpeak in the</hi> Jews <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; and I contended with them and curſed them, and ſmote certain of them, and plucked off their hair, and made them ſwear by God, ſaying, Ye ſhall not give your Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to their Sons, &amp;c.</hi> Nehem. 13.11, 15, 18, 21, 24, 25. How zealous alſo was <hi>Aſa</hi> in his Reformation, where he ſpared not his own Mother, but removed her from being Queen, becauſe ſhe had made an Idol in a Grove, and <hi>Aſa</hi> cut down her Idoll, and ſtamped it and burnt it at the Brook <hi>Kidron?</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15, 16. And the ſame
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37143:9"/>
Apoſtle that enjoins moderation in the Text, tells us alſo, <hi>That it is good to be zealouſly affected alwaies in a good thing.</hi> Galat. 4 18. and<note n="(e)" place="margin">Nullum omnipotenti deo tale eſt ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium, quale eſt zelus animarum. Paulo poſt; ſunt mnita bona, quae aguntur ſacrificia, ſed holo cauſtum non ſunt, quia totam mentem in amore spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuali minimè incendunt. <hi>Greg.</hi> ſuper <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the zeal of the Soul is the moſt acceptable Sacrifice to God, and makes other Sacrifices to become whole-burnt-offerings unto the Lord.</hi> God can leſs endure Lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſs, than if a man were altogether cold; for, ſpeaking after the manner of men, ſaith he to the Church of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicea, I would thou wert cold or hot, ſo then, becauſe thou art lukewarm, and neither cold nor hot, I will ſpue thee out of my mouth, Rev.</hi> 3.15, 16. Will you ſay, he is a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man, who can hear the Glorious name of God and his Son Jeſus Chriſt blaſphemed, and yet his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit not boyle within him, with a mixture of anger and grief thereat? is he a moderate man, that ſhall ſuffer himſelf to be drawn away to hereſie or idolatry, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any reſiſtance, when Enticers to Idolatry, how near ſoever, were to be put to death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1. Or am I moderate man, if being a Parent, Maſter of a Family, or a Miniſter, ſhall permit an Anabaptiſt, an Arrian, Arminian or Papiſt to come and ſow their ſeeds of Errors in my Family and Pariſh, thereby to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce my people? Certainly, in ſuch caſes as this, a great meaſure of zeal is neceſſary, and ſome extravagancies are excuſable, as being errors <hi>ardentis amoris:</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that of <hi>Moſes</hi> is obſervable, who <hi>having been in the Mount with God, and received from him the Law in two Tables, comming down and beholding the Idolatry of the people, his anger waxed hot, and he caſt the Tables out of his hands and brake them beneath the Mount,</hi> Exod. 32.19. wherein thongh <hi>Moſes</hi> was blame-worthy yet the Scripture doth not blame him, ſo well doth God like of zeal in ſuch caſes.<note place="margin">Joel. 2.13</note> Rending of Garments were in uſe amongſt the <hi>Jews</hi> at the Report of blaſphemy, and no where that I find condemned; only we are warned to rend the heart more than the Garment, and if any one ſhould cenſure a man for rending his Garments, or ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37143:10"/>
like action in theſe dayes at the hearing of blaſphemie, I think he were no leſs to blame than <hi>Eli,</hi> for paſſing the cenſure of drunkenneſs upon ſorrowfull <hi>Hannah;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13, 14.</note> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that of the Apoſtle, that if a man in this caſe, to outward appearance, be beſides himſelf, it is for God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. Will ye call him a moderate man, who living amongſt vicious perſons, given to drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſwearing, prophanation of Gods day, and ſuch like groſs impieties, is nothing affected therewith? then <hi>Lot</hi> was an immoderate man, whoſe righteous ſoul was vexed from day to day with the unlawfull deeds of the <hi>Sodomites:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</note> much more <hi>David,</hi> whoſe eyes ran down with Rivers of tears,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.</note> becauſe men did not keep Gods Law. That therefore is not moderation, but luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſſe, which the Lord doth highly abominate and abhorre.</p>
            <p>Only miſtake me not; I ſay, a moderate man is not luke-warm in thoſe things, wherein Gods glory is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned; Otherwiſe, if the thing be indifferent, he is alſo indifferent, and where the thing is neither good nor evil, he is neither cold nor hot; but in matters of weight and importance, there is none more zealous than he: For indeed, he thriftily treaſured up his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits againſt ſuch a time, who if he had formerly ſpent his Lungs about every trifle, would have wanted breath to plead for things of greater concernment. Moderation therefore and luke-warmneſs do exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly differ; the luke-warm man eyeth his own ends and particular profit, the moderate man aims at the Good of others, and the unitie of the Church: the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man is indifferent in things which are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; but the luke-warm perſon is indifferent in things which concern the glory of God: the moderate man is full of charity, which makes him luke-warm in things which are mere circumſtantial; the luke-warm perſon is empty of piety, which makes him luke-warm in things which are altogether ſubſtantial.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Moderation is not a toleration of things which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37143:10"/>
are deſtructive unto the eſſence or foundation of the doctrine and worſhip of true Chriſtian Religion. In things of leſſer moment there is no man more ſuffering than he, he will ſuffer others to uſe their liberty, yea he will abridge himſelf of his own liberty, rather than be an occaſion of caſting any mans conſcience into ſtraits. In ſuch things he ſaith, as the Apoſtle, 1 Cor. 11.16. <hi>If any man ſeem to be contentious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God.</hi> If ye look at the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree from whence Contention is extracted, you ſhall eaſily perceive, that Moderation is nothing a kin to it. I think<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>W. Q.</hi> in a Sermon on <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>11.16.</hi>
               </note> he ſpake not amiſs, who ſaid; <q>There was a baſtard begotten by anger, nurſed by pride, and maintained by wilfull contradiction, and when they came to give him a name, they called him Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And, as was the name of the child, ſo was his nature, for as ſoon as ever he began to goe, he went backward, like the Sea-crab; as ſoon as ever he began to read, he read backward, like the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> as ſoon as he began to row, he rowed backward, evermore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Tide and Stream.</q> If this be the nature of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, it is altogether contrary to Moderation, which in matters of indifferencie will yeeld far to, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply much with others.</p>
            <p>But if it be a thing that tends to the ſubverſion of the ſubſtance and foundation of Religion derogating from the perſon or office of Chriſt, the mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man; Gods free Grace in him; that full redemption wrought, and ſalvation purchaſed by him; that exact obedience and abundant thanks, which we owe to him for this work; or any other fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal principle of the doctrine of Chriſt; this a moderate man will by no means tolerate, <hi>for he can do nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.8. and for that faith, which <hi>was once delivered to the Saints, he will earneſtly contend,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude, v. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>againſt all that creep in unawares, bringing in damnable hereſies, ungodly men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>turning the grace of our God into laſciviouſneſs, and denying the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37143:11"/>
bought them.</hi> He thinks a toleration in this ſenſe, to be ſo far from Religion, that it is againſt the very light of nature; as is apparent from <hi>Moſes</hi> his reply to <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oh;</hi> when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> called for <hi>Moſes</hi> and for <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Go ye ſacrifice to your God in the land;</hi> Moſes <hi>ſaid, it is not meet ſo to do, for we ſhall ſacrifice the abomination of the</hi> Egyptians <hi>to the Lord our God: ſhall we ſacrifice the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of the</hi> Egyptians <hi>before their eys, and will they not stone us?</hi> Exo. 8.25, 26. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, to the Church of <hi>Pergamos, becauſe thou haſt there the doctrine of</hi> Balaam, <hi>thou haſt alſo the doctrine of the</hi> Nicolaitans, <hi>which thing I hate,</hi> Rev. 2.14, 15. So ſaith he to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Thyatira, I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman</hi> Jezabel <hi>to teach and to ſeduce my ſervants,</hi> Rev. 2.20. A toleratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch doctrins &amp; manners, as the Lord hates, is moſt intolerable. We read in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.6. of a <hi>Woe to the pot, whoſe ſcum is therein, and whoſe ſcum is not gone out of it;</hi> But where there is a toleration, I cannot ſee how the ſcum can be purged out; and certainly, where Magiſtrates &amp; Miniſters will not be at the pains to take off this ſcum, the Lord himſelf will do it, but it ſhall be in a fearfull manner. <hi>Therfore thus ſaith the Lord God, Woe to the bloudie Citie, I will even make the pile of fire great, heap on wood, kindle the fire, conſume the fleſh, and spice it well, and let the bones be burnt: then ſet it empty upon the coals thereof, that the braſs of it may be hot, and may burn, and that the filthineſs of it may be molten in it, that the ſcum of it may be conſumed,</hi> Ezek. 24.9, 10, 11. <hi>Andronicus,</hi> though in other things bad enough, yet in this was good and imitable, that he would not abide to hear any fundamental point of Religion brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to queſtion; inſomuch, that when once two Biſhops began to contend about the meaning of that noted place, <hi>My Father is greater than I; Andronicus,</hi> ſuſpecting that they would fall foul upon the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> hereſie, vowed to throw them both into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, except they would be quiet. A way (ſaith my
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37143:11"/>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Mr. Fuller.</note> learned Author, to quench the hotteſt diſputation, by an inartificial anſwer, drawn from ſuch authoritie. That is a very remarkable paſſage, which<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ammian. Marcell. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ Juliani, quoted by Mr. Baxter in his Eternal reſt, part. <hi>1.</hi> ch. <hi>7.</hi> ſect. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ammia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Marcellinus</hi> makes mention of concerning <hi>Julian,</hi> the greateſt Apoſtate from, and Enemie unto the the Church of God in thoſe times; when he could not bring about his deſired ends by a violent perſecution, he proclamed Libertie (ſaith he) for every partie to profeſs and preach their own opinions, becauſe hee thought this would make Chriſtians fall out one with another, and ruine themſelves, which he by all his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions could not effect, ſo long as they held and ſtrove together with one mind for the faith of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; And ſo by Libertie of Conſcience (ſaith he) and by keeping their children from the Schools of learning, he thought to have rooted out Chriſtianitie from the earth. It is an obſervable paſſage, and I ſhall only give you this Comment upon it; that it is a very ſad thing, when we ſhall make uſe of the moſt exquiſit and deep-ſtudied plots and projects of our greateſt enemies, to raiſe the Church, which they made uſe of to ruine it: God, I know, can by his infinite power and wiſdom, bring order out of confuſion, and light out of darkneſs; but however, this courſe is in it ſelf neither pious, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, nor ſafe: for not Gods unknown power, but his known will is the rule that we muſt walk by. Thus you ſee, what Moderation is not, it is neither Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tralitie, Luke-warmneſs, nor a Toleration, in that ſenſe I have ſhewed you. I preſume, that all theſe will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and boldly challenge kinred with Moderation; but it wholly diſclaims them, as the baſe offſpring and brood of carnal policie; and not the true children iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing from a ſound judgement in matters of faith, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere pietie toward God, and unfeigned charity toward our Brethren, as Moderation doth. As well may ye call prodigalitie liberalitie, covetouſneſs good hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, and pride neatneſſe; as call either Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Lukewarmneſs, or a toleration, by the name of Moderation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37143:12"/>Having ſhewed you, what Moderation is not, I come now to ſhew you, as near as I can, what it is; and ye may take this deſcription of it in the general.<note place="margin">What Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is.</note> It is a grace, whereby we are enabled in all quarrels, cauſes and Conditions, ſo to carry our ſelves, as not to offend God, or give any unjuſt offence to men. A Grace that keeps us from extravagancies and extremes. Now this Moderation may be conſidered three wayes, in the judgement, in the affection, and in the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">1. In the judgement.</note>1. Moderation in the Judgement is a mixture of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion &amp; charity in ones judgement. <q>Diſcretion (ſaith Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi>) puts a difference between things abſolutely neceſſary to be done and believed unto Salvation, and thoſe w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are of a ſecond ſort, &amp; lower form, wherein more liberty and latitude is allowed, in maintaining whereof the ſtiffneſs of the judgement is abated and ſuppled, with charity towards his neighbour.</q> A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man hath his ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern of things which are formal,<note place="margin">5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 14.</note> and things which are funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, &amp; knows that it is the maintaining of a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental eror, which mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs a man a heretick, nor is it the meer maintaining, but the obſtinat maintaining ſuch an error, that givs a man the odious name of Heretick: <q>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy is the dead fleſh, which maks the green wound of an an error, to feſter into the old ſore of an Hereſie.</q> The moderate man conſiders that ſome differences of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions are, as<note n="(i)" place="margin">Lord <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> in his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of learn.</note> one elegantly expreſſeth it, as the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of one Iſraelite with another, and theſe <hi>Moſes</hi> quiets, and parts them fairly; but other <hi>viz.</hi> Hereſies fighting againſt the foundation, are like the Aegyptians fighting with the Iſraelite, whom <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmites down. 2 <hi>Exod.</hi> The moderate man diſtinguiſheth of Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and erroneous perſons, as<note n="(k)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> in his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a good Biſhop.</note> Phyſicians do of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous people; ſome are infectious, others which have the Leproſie called <hi>Elephantiaſis,</hi> are not infectious; ſome are active to ſeduce others, others quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their opinions in their own conſciences; the latter
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37143:12"/>
by his mildneſs he eaſily reduceth to the truth; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Chirurgions rigorous handling of it, often breaks the bone quite off, which formerly was but out of joint: Towards the former he uſeth more ſeverity, yet endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring firſt to inform them aright, before he cauſe them to be puniſhed; for to uſe force firſt, before peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are fairly taught the truth, is to knock a nail into a board, without wimbling an hole for it, which then either not enters, or turns crooked, or ſplits the wood it pierceth.</p>
            <p>A moderate man doth not, like the two Diſciples, preſently call for fire from heaven upon an Heretick; he would not have him preſently puniſhed, much leſs put to death; yet he would have him reſtrained, that he may not ſeduce: for ye will not ſuffer a man that hath a running plague-ſore, to go abroad to infect, though his ſhutting up be not in way of puniſhment, as if he were puniſhed, becauſe he hath the ſore, but in way of prevention of contagion, as the reſtraint of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per was under the Law; and if he will not be reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but obſtinately perſiſt in his error, labouring to ſeduce others, then the moderate perſon thinks, he is not any longer gently to be forborn, but more roughly dealt with; for he will not be ſo charitable to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of an heretick, as to countenance his error, and prejudice the truth of Chriſt, which is of more value than any mans life. <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is kind, yet it rejoyceth not in iniquity, but rejoyceth in the truth.</hi> 1 Cor. 13.4.6.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> in a Sermon, <hi>2</hi> Pet. <hi>2.1.</hi>
               </note> Some argue againſt the puniſhment of Hereticks with death, becauſe it is meerly an intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual error: Now, ſay they, you would not hang a Phyſician for a murtherer, who upon a miſtake gives his patient a potion of poyſon inſtead of good medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, nor a mad-man that breaks out, and ſlays and kills ſuch as he meets with, becauſe this proceeds from the laeſion of his underſtanding: Now (ſaith Mr. <hi>Vines</hi>) though I do not concurre with this ſuppoſal, that hereſie is a meer act of the underſtanding, for it hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37143:13"/>
its denomination from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an act of the Wil chuſing the error; yet thus far I go with it, that ſuch pretended Phyſicians, as hold that to be poiſon which is whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and on the contrary, are not to be licenſed to practiſe, nor ſuch mad men ſuffered to exerciſe their fury. And if ſuch a Phyſician ſhall, after he is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to practiſe, yet go on, and in the exerciſe thereof kill a man, I ſee no reaſon at all why he ſhould not be put to death, as one guilty of murther; for tho it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ignorance, yet it is a pertinacious ignorance.</p>
            <p>In a word therefore, a moderate judgement is a judgement well-weighed with truth and love, one that is neither credulous nor cenſorious. A moderate man will not have any mans perſon in ſuch admiration or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, as thereby to be drawn to an approbation of his errors; for ſo he ſhall wrong the truth, and wrong his own judgement; yet however he hate the error, he hath a charitable opinion of the perſon that holds it, and walks according to it, ſo it be not with obſtinacy, and a deſire to ſeduce, conceiving that he is miſled through ignorance, and upon better information will recant: And if the error be in things of leſs moment, that are meerly circumſtantial, he bears with him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, being willing that he ſhould ſpeak as a child, and underſtand as a child, and think as a child, till he come to more maturity of underſtanding,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11.</note> remembring that of the Apoſtle, <hi>That the ſtrong ought to bear the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities of the weak, and not to pleaſe themſelves,</hi> Rom. 15.1. Contrary therefore to this moderate judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſay, is firſt a credulous judgement in the defect, which is apt upon the good opinion it hath of ſuch a mans perſon, with better liking to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain his errors, whether in Doctrine or practice, and to think, certainly there is not ſo much poiſon in them, becauſe adminiſtred by ſuch a perſon. This though it doth argue much honeſty, yet it doth alſo argue much weakneſs. Charity is commendable, but not this credulity; I will never be ſo charitable to any,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37143:13"/>
as to wrong my own judgement and the truth, out of a good affection that I bear to any mans perſon.<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypriani</hi> literas non ut canonicas ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, ſed ex ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicis conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, &amp; quod in iis divinarum Scripturarum autoritati con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruit cum lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ejus accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o, quod autem non congruit, cum pace e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus reſpuo. <hi>Aug.</hi> adv. Creſcon. lib. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> practice in this is worrhy our imitation; <hi>I do not hold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the writings of</hi> Cyprian <hi>(though a famous, godly, and learned Martyr) for canonical, but I compare them with thoſe that are canonical, and what I find in them agreeable to the authority of divine writ, I do with his praiſe receive, but what I find doth not agree with the Scripture, I do with his leave refuſe.</hi> 2. Contrary to this moderate judgement, is a cenſorious judgement, and this reſpects a mans perſon, as the other did his error. A credulous man is apt too much to like the Error for the Perſon ſake; the cenſorious too much to diſlike the Perſons for the Errors ſake: now the moderate man goes between both; he likes not the Error one jot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the Perſons ſake, no more than he would poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon preſented in a Golden Cup; neither doth he at the firſt much more diſlike the Perſon for the Errors ſake, till he ſee him proudly obſtinate in his Error after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and take up a looſe and carnal courſe of life in patronage of his Error, then indeed he ſhakes hands with him, as one departed from the Church, yet with Prayers, that he may rerurn again. A cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement therefore I call that, which is too raſh, too harſh. 1. Too raſh, <hi>Iudging things before the time.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4, 5. Iudging what men will be, before they profeſs themſelves to be ſo, and what they will do, before they do it. A wiſely ſuſpicious judgment is commendable, but a raſhly cenſorious is to be condemned. 2. Too harſh, in judging of mens affections and conditions towards God by one or two unjuſtifiable actions.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 9 <hi>&amp;</hi> 10 <hi>cha.</hi>
               </note> For I am ſo charitable as to think, that as <hi>Jehu</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſe, and the Idolatry thereof, which was a good action, with a corrupt intention; ſo may good men ſometimes do unjuſtifiable actions, yet with a ſincere and upright intention. Now as he errs in the one hand, that ſhould go about any way to juſtifie their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; ſo he erres no leſs in the other, that doth ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37143:14"/>
cenſure and condemn their perſons and their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, before they profeſs themſelves to be ſuch. Hence it is, that we are in Scripture ſo much warnd to to take heed of judging. <hi>Judge not, that ye be not judged,</hi> Mat. 7.1. <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy Brother, let us not judge one another any more.</hi> Rom. 14.10, 13. <hi>Iudge nothing before the time, untill the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will manifeſt the counſels of the heart,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.5. <hi>For though ſome mens ſins are open before hand going before to judgement, yet ſome mens they follow after,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.24. They are ſo ſecret or elſe ſo ſpecious, that they muſt be referred wholly to the judgment of the laſt day. The ſum of all is this, a moderate man, though he be not ſo judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al or judging as to wrong others; yet he is ſo judicious as not to wrong himſelf, or wrong the truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, this Moderation in the judgement is a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of diſcretion and charity.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Moderation in the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>2. This Moderation may be conſidered in the Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and that is, when a Chriſtian is ſeriouſly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, and thereupon doth hate and grieve for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills and errors practiſed and profeſſed by others, yet with much meekneſs. Firſt, I ſay, when he doth hate the evills and errors practiſed and profeſſed by others. <hi>Ye that love the Lord hate evill,</hi> Pſal. 97.10. <hi>I hate the works of them that turn aſide,</hi> ſaith David, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 101.3. <hi>I hate every falſe way,</hi> Pſal. 119.104. And the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> how ever ſhe was in ſome things defective, having left her firſt love, yet ſaith Chriſt, <hi>this thou haſt, that thou hateſt the deeds of the</hi> Nicolaitanes, <hi>which I alſo hate.</hi> Rev. 2.6. Again, I ſay, a moderate man, as he hates, ſo he grieves for the evills and errors of others, <hi>When I came to</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>ſaith</hi> Nehemiah, <hi>and understood of the evill that</hi> Elia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhib <hi>did for</hi> Tobiah, <hi>in preparing him a Chamber in the Courts of the houſe of God, it grieved me ſore, and I caſt forth all the Houſhold-ſtuff of</hi> Tobiah <hi>out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Nehe.</hi> 13.7.8. Every Chriſtian may be thus grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37143:14"/>
as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was, when ſuch evills are done, though perhaps they have neither power nor authority to rectifie them. <hi>I beheld the transgreſſors and was grieved</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) becauſe they kept not thy word,</hi> Pſal. 119.158. <hi>and</hi> Pſalm 139.21. <hi>Am not I grieved with thoſe that riſe up againſt thee?</hi> There is but little love in that man to God, who doth not grieve at that which grieves God. But then in the laſt place, I ſay, the Moderate man, though he do ſeriouſly hate and grieve for the evills and the errors done and declared by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet it is with much Chriſtian meekneſs, without wrath and rancor, ſo far as humane infirmity will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. <hi>I know thy works</hi> (ſaith Chriſt <hi>to the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus) <hi>and thy labour, and thy patience, and how thou canst not bear them which are evill, and haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my name ſake haſt laboured and haſt not fainted.</hi> Rev. 2.2, 3. This is a moſt notable place to our purpoſe; I know thy Labour and thy Patience, how thou haſt born, and haſt Patience, and yet canſt bear them which are evill. This might ſeem to be a manifeſt contradiction; but it is not; for it becomes a moderate Miniſter or Chriſtian with all his might to ſtrive to redreſs ſuch evills, as are within the compaſs of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and calling, and what he cannot redreſs, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to endure, being ſenſible of them, hating them, and grieving for them, but not moved thereby unto a fretting impatience, either againſt God or man. Thou canſt not bear them which are evill, and yet haſt born, and haſt patience, and for my name ſake haſt laboured and not fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Lord will render unto every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his work, <hi>to them who by patient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuace in well doing ſeek for glorie and honour and immortality, eternall life: but unto them that are contentious, and do not obey the truth, but obey un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightouſneſſe, indignation and wrath.</hi> Rom. 2.6, 7, 8. So the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> having declared the wickedneſſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37143:15"/>
and oppreſſion of rich men, which was not in the power of poor men to redreſſe; <hi>Be patient therefore,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>brethren, unto the coming of the Lord, be ye alſo patient, ſtabliſh your hearts, for the coming of the Lord draweth nigh; Grudge not one againſt another, leſt ye be condemned; behold the Judge ſtandeth before the door; take the Prophets, who have ſpoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, we count them happie which endure,</hi> James 5.7, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>If when you do well, and ſuffer for it patiently, this is acceptable unto God</hi> 1 Pet. 2.20.</p>
            <p>Contrary to this Moderation in the Affections, in the defect, is 1. when men are not ſenſible of, nor doe they cordially hate and grieve for the evils and errors of others, how loud and clamorous ſoever they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. So I obſerve many, who are very inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive againſt the corruptions, innovations and hereſies of the times, who yet are nothing affected with the diſhonour that is done to God by them, and the decay of religion. As in that uproar, which <hi>Demetrius</hi> raiſed, <hi>ſome cried one thing, and ſome another, and the aſſembly was confuſed, for the more part knew not wherefore they were come together,</hi> Acts 19.32. So is it among our people, generally they are confuſed, ſome crie out againſt the Sects, hereſies, and corruptions of the times for one thing, ſome for another, and the greater part know not wherfore, only becauſe that they hear others. Some ther are again, who profeſs to deteſt and be griev'd at the corruptions of the times, but it is out of a politick re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, as the Jews, <hi>Jo.</hi> 11.48. oppoſed Chriſt, <hi>If we let him thus alone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Timemus ne ſubvertamur, de ignominia verò Christi omnium mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me dolemus, <hi>Muſc.</hi> ſuper Joan. cap. <hi>2.</hi> v, <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> ſay they, <hi>all men will believe on him, and the</hi> Romans <hi>ſhall come and take away both our place and nation.</hi> So they, if we let theſe Sectaries alone thus, not the truth of God ſhall fall in the Streets and be trodden under foot, the Church rooted out, Gods worſhip deſtroyed; no, but they will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to an head, over-runne us, take away our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates from us, and exerciſe tyrannie over us. This is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37143:15"/>
the Ground of the grief of knowing worldly Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not that they care for the promotion of the Church, or the propagation of the Goſpel; yet now they profeſs to ſtand for them; the reaſon is, becauſe the preſent intereſt of the Church, is ſomething linked with their own intereſt, and they do but contend for the former with relation to the latter: For were the Church and they at reſt from the preſent diſturbers of our peace, ye ſhould have it as much vexed and grieved with the ſcoffings and prophaneneſs of theſe men, as now it is with the ſchiſms and hereſies of the other. 2. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this Moderation of the Affections in the exceſſe, is wrath and ſwelling. Though others do evil, yet that is no warrant for us to do evil. <hi>Fret not thy ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the man who bringeth wicked devices to paſs, ceaſe from anger, and forſake wrath; fret not thy ſelf in any wiſe to do evil, for evill doers ſhall be cut off, but thoſe that wait upon the Lord, ſhall inherit the earth,</hi> Pſ. 37.7, 8, 9. wrath and envying are numbred among the works of the fleſh, as well as ſeditions and hereſies, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20, 21. and we are commanded to put off wrath, anger and malice, as well as blaſphemy, they being no leſſe deeds of the old man, and members of the body of death, than the other, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.8. Sure it is, the <hi>wrath of man doth not work the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> James 1.20. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is meekneſs ſo much commended in Scripture, as an <hi>ornament of great price in the ſight of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.4. And we are commanded, in evil times, when the fierce anger of the Lord is breaking out, <hi>to ſeek righteouſneſſe, to ſeek meekneſſe, if that we deſire to be hid in the day of the Lords wrath,</hi> Zeph: 2.2, 3. Unto meekneſſe it is, that ſo many promiſes are made, <hi>the meek ſhall inherit the earth, and ſhall delight themſelves in the abundance of</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, if they want outward) <hi>peace,</hi> Pſ. 37.11. <hi>The Lord lifteth up the meek,</hi> Pſal. 147.6. <hi>He will beautifie the meek with ſalvation,</hi> Pſal. 149.4. <hi>The meek alſo ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their joy in the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 29.19. It is a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to our profeſſion, and ſtops the mouths of falſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37143:16"/>
1 Pet. 3.14. <hi>If ye ſuffer for righteouſneſſe ſake, happy are ye, and be not afraid of their terrors, neither be troubled, but ſanctifie the Lord God in your hearts, and be ready alwaies to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, that whereas they ſpeak evil of you, they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, who falſly accuſe your good converſation in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Moderation in the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</note>3. This Moderation may be conſidered in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and that is, when a man out of zeal to Gods Glory, keeping himſelf within the compaſs of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, doth ſpeak and act againſt the evils and errors of the times he lives in, and the perſons he lives amongſt, be they never ſo great; yet with much modeſty and reverence, eſpecially if they be great. Now contrary to this, 1. in the defect is, when men doe not or dare not, according to the duty of their general or particular callings, declare their diſlike and deteſtation of the evils and corruptions of the times and places they live in. This proceeds from baſe puſillanimous fear and cowardiſe of ſpirit; whereas we are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>not to fear their fear, neither to be afraid, but to ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts himſelf, and let him be our fear, and let him be our dread, and he ſhall be for a Sanctuary.</hi> Iſa. 8.12, 13. <hi>The fearfull and unbelieving ſhall have their part in the Lake, that burns with fire and brimſton,</hi> Revel. 21.8. This Chriſt takes for no better than a denial of him, as appears by the oppoſition, Mat. 12.32, 33. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall confeſs me before men, him will I alſo confeſſe before my father, which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but whoſoever ſhall deny me before men, him will I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deny before my father, which is in heaven.</hi> Not openly to confeſs Chriſt therefore, is to deny him, <hi>and if we deny him, he will alſo deny us,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.12. It is ſaid of thoſe that received the mark of the beaſt, that <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it in their right hand,</hi> Rev. 13.16. a place which they might either open or ſhut; and ſo either cover or diſcover the mark, when they pleaſed: but thoſe that receive the mark of the lamb, Chriſt Jeſus, have it in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37143:16"/>
their foreheads, a place open and obvious to the view of all men, in teſtimony that they are not aſhamed of Chriſt, and will not either for fear or favour diſſemble him. For this you have an excellent place, <hi>Iſay</hi> 44.5. <hi>One ſhall ſay, I am the Lords, and another ſhall call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by the name of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, and ſurname himſelf by the name of</hi> Iſrael: Such ſhall be their undanted courage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution for God, that they ſhall not be afraid to make profeſſion in ſo many words, <hi>I am the Lords,</hi> and to ſubſcribe their name to it, when they had done. Now, this doth eſpecially concern Miniſters, who are pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſet up by God, <hi>To cry aloud, to lift up their voice like a Trumpet, and to ſhew the people their ſins,</hi> Iſa. 58.1. <hi>Whom God hath ſet over Nations and Kingdoms, to reot out, and to pull down, and to deſtroy, and to throw down, and to build, and to plant,</hi> Jer. 1.10. <hi>Whom God hath deputed in his ſtead to judge, yea to judge whole Nations for their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, and to cauſe them to know their abominations,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 20.4. <hi>And therefore they of all others ſhould not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of, or diſmaid at the faces of men, leſt the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them before the people.</hi> Jer. 1.8, 17. They ſhould not <hi>be afraid of the words, nor diſmaid at the looks of men, be they never ſo rebellious, be they as ſharp as thorns and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and ſtinging as Scorpions,</hi> Ezech. 2.6, 7. but ſhould, with <hi>Peter,</hi> teſtifie and exhort, ſaying, <hi>ſave your ſelves from this untoward generation,</hi> Act. 2.40.</p>
            <p>And as it doth concern Miniſters eſpecially, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their particular calling, ſo it doth concern all men, in reſpect of their general calling, to declare their diſlike of the corruptions and evils of the times and places they live in; <hi>having no fellowſhip with the unfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full works of darkneſs, but rather reproving them,</hi> Epheſ. 5.11. withdrawing themſelves from all ſuch, as are of corrupt minds, deſtitute of the truth, as we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>marking them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the doctrine which they have learned, and avoiding them, for they that are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37143:17"/>
ſuch, ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own belly, and by good words and fair ſpeeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple,</hi> Rom. 16.17, 18. <hi>That ſo they may be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and harmleſs, the ſons of God without rebuke, in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe Nation, among whom they ſhine as lights in the world,</hi> Phil. 2.15.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As fearfull cowardiſe is contrary to Moderation in defect, ſo Turbulency is contrary to it in the exceſs: and that is twofold, either in words or actions. 1. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulency in words: It is noted by St. <hi>Peter</hi> of thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Enthuſiaſts, which he ſpeaks of, that <hi>they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. and <hi>Jude</hi> notes the ſame thing of them alſo, <hi>That their mouth ſpeaketh great ſwelling words, and uttereth hard ſpeeches,</hi> v. 15.16. theſe hard ſpeeches and ſwelling words are for the moſt part uttered againſt Magiſtrates and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; as <hi>Korah,</hi> with his company, gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and againſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſaid unto them, <hi>Ye take too much upon you, ſeeing all the Congregation are holy, every one of them, and the Lord is among them; wherefore then lift ye up your ſelves above the Congregation of the Lord,</hi> Numb. 16.3. This is the direct language of turbulent and ſchiſmaticall perſons; and indeed it is the Lord <hi>Verulam</hi>'s note, that if any new ſect hath not two properties, it is not to be feared that it will ſpread; the one is the ſupplanting or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Authority eſtabliſhed; for nothing is more populous than that; the other is, giving licenſe to pleaſures, and a voluptuous courſe of life. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let thoſe, which profeſs themſelves ſuch enemies to Sectaries (not their perſons, but their opinions) take heed that by their practice they do not approve of them in this particular.</p>
            <p>Sure it is, the tongue is a moſt unruly member, and is not ſo eaſily tamed, as the ſtomachfull horſe, or guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the unweildy ſhip; it boaſteth great things, and is full of deadly poiſon, no man can tame it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.3.4. And it is ſtrange to ſee, what liberty ſome men (who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37143:17"/>
pretend conſcience) will aſſume unto themſelves in this; whereas it is ſaid that <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, when he contended with the Devil about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> durſt not bring a railing accuſation againſt him, but ſaid, <hi>the Lord rebuke thee,</hi> Jude 1.9. The truth is, railing is one of the laſt and baſeſt unworthy ſhifts of a needy perſon, and it is to be feared, he who uſeth it, hath no better weapon. Therefore <hi>Paul</hi> gives <hi>Titus</hi> charge, to put them in mind to be ſubject to principalities and powers, to obey Magiſtrates, to ſpeak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs to all men, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1, 2. That was as moderate, yet a reſolute anſwer, which the three Children gave to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar: If it be ſo, our God whom we ſerve, is able to deliver us out of this fiery fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace, and he will, but if not, be it known unto thee, O King</hi> (not O Tyrant, or Perſecuter) <hi>that we will not ſerve thy God, nor worſhip the graven Image which thou haſt ſet up,</hi> Dan. 3.17, 18. Alike moderate, and yet reſolute, was the anſwer of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Electour of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> who being priſoner to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, was promiſed inlargement, and reſtitution of dignity, if he would come to Maſs, <hi>Summum in terris Dominum agnoſco Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarem, in Coelis Deum;</hi> In all earthly matters I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Caeſar</hi> as ſupream, but in heavenly God. We are not to revile any, much leſſe the Gods of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſuch hot tongues as are bliſtered with this venom, ſurely are ſet on fire of hell, and are far from this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.</p>
            <p>Again, certainly, ſo much bitterneſs even in the juſt proſecution of the Sects and errors of our times, muſt needs be condemned; and yet what a deal of it may one meet with in the Preſs, and ſometimes in the Pulpit: ſo much virulency and bitterneſs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13, 14.</note> as if the poyſon of Aſpes were under their lips, their mouthes are ſo full of curſing and bitterneſs. This doth more inrage, but nothing more reclaim them, who are given to ſchiſm and innovation, who are more proud, the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37143:18"/>
more proudly they are oppoſed, and come to encreaſe, and be well liked of amongſt ignorant people, as perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted men, becauſe of ſuch bitter oppoſition. A fool muſt not be altogether unanſwered; yet he muſt not be anſwered fooliſhly, for then we are like unto him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4, 5. Now there is nothing wherein a wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man doth more bewray folly, than in being bitter, when he is in juſt contention with a fool; it is but a ſorry victory that a man gets by conquering of a fool, but if whilſt he ſtrive with a fool, he can but rule his own ſpirit, that is a victory indeed, more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the taking of a City, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.32. otherwiſe, be the cauſe never ſo ſtrong that a man defends, if he be paſſionate, he is weak; and his weakneſs will his adverſary (though without cauſe) be ready to caſt as an aſperſion upon his cauſe; and ignorant people who have but little skill of controverſie, are in their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons led for the moſt part by the actions of the perſons, their Logick lying alltogether in inartificial arguments; as <hi>Jovinian</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Arrian</hi> and orthodox Biſhops, contending for the faith, Of your learning &amp; ſubtle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations, I cannot ſo well judge; but I can well marke and obſerve, which of your behaviours is moſt peaceable and fruitfull: So your ordinary people are not ſo able to judge of mens parts, nor of the queſtion that is in diſpute; but they can eaſily ſee whoſe carriage is moſt ſober, peaceable, and plauſible; and their rule, moſt what is to judge of the cauſe by the perſons. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is one mark of a fool; <hi>Anger reſteth in the boſome of fools.</hi> Eccl. 7.9. and Prov. 27.3. <hi>A ſtone is heavy, and the ſand weighty, but a fools wrath is heavier than them both.</hi> As a man that is light in his head with drink, or with a diſeaſe, if he chance to fall, goes ſo much more ſadly and heavily to the ground, not able to ſtay or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour himſelf in his fall; ſo it is with a fool, the reaſon why his wrath is ſo heavy, is becauſe his head is ſo light, and he hath not reaſon to counterpoiſe his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. When a wiſe man therefore contending with a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37143:18"/>
fool, ſhall break out into unſeemly paſſion, what can one ſay? As <hi>Demonax,</hi> when he ſaw one cruel in the beating of his ſervant, Fie (ſaith he) forbear, leſt by the world you be taken for the ſervant: So it may be ſaid to a wiſe man, in rage ſtriving with a fool; fie, forbear, leſt by the world you be taken for the fool. Nothing doth ſo befool a man, as extream paſſion, this doth make men fools, that otherwiſe are not, and ſhew them to be fools that are ſo: if we cannot tame vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſions; that they may yeeld to our eaſe, we ſhould labour at leaſt to ſmother them by concealment, that they may not appear to our ſhame. I confeſs indeed, a wiſe man dealing with a fool, goes upon much diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage one way; he ſhall be ſure to have many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations unto paſſion, his irrational reaſons, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous anſwers, and groundleſs diſtinctions, with his te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Circumlocutions, muſt needs be very irkſom and unpleaſing to a judicious man: and when a fool pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds a queſtion, and it come to be diſcuſſed, he ſhall, as moſt what he doth, flie from the matter, refuſing to be kept within any limits, this is a very great provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; and his extravagancie in the Action, makes his Opponent ſometimes extravagant in his paſſion: but a wiſe and moderate man, knowing that he muſt expect no fair dealing from a fool, ſhould therefore arm himſelf accordingly before-hand with humble prayer to God, and ſtrong reſolution within himſelf; <hi>ſaying that he will,</hi> and praying that he may, <hi>take heed to his ways, that he ſin not with his tongue, but keep his mouth as with a bridle, whilſt the wicked is before him,</hi> Pſal. 39.1. I doe not ſee how a wiſe man, when he flies from the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he is contending about, to fall upon the perſon that he contends with, can clear himſelf before God or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men. When a man contends with a fool, he doth not ſo much contend againſt him, as his errour, for who, elſe, would trouble himſelf with a fool? When a wiſe man therefore in the heat of contention ſhall ſo far forget himſelf, as to leave the proſecution of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37143:19"/>
queſtion, to fall upon the perſon, ſurely this is more diſtempered heat than zeal; for he hath now ſtrayed and gone from the buſineſſe; and he, that makes the fool, and not his folly, the Butt that he ſhoots at, doth undoubtedly miſſe the mark: ſo he may wound the perſon and make the fool rage, but leaves the errour untouched. Again, when a mans paſſion boiles ſo within him, as to ſend forth the ſcum of evil language, or the froth of uncivil taunts againſt his adverſary, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly he hath tranſgreſſed the bounds of Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Neither railing nor lightneſſe become a wiſe man, any more than a grave parable doth a fool. A fool will rage and rail, but what then? do ye expect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny better from a briar, than that it ſhould ſcratch? Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe will proceed from the wicked, as ſaith the proverb of the Antients, but a wiſe man will keep off his hand, and keep up his tongue, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.13. knowing, that if reaſon will not convince his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, raiſing will but more exaſperate and obdurate him. To ſhut up this, the moderate man (if God ſee it good) <hi>deſireth life, and loveth many dayes, that he may ſee good,</hi> (and do much good) and therfore <hi>keepeth his tongue from evil, and his lips from speaking guile,</hi> Pſal. 34.12, 13. <hi>not rendring evil for evil, or railing for railing, but contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe bleſſing, knowing that he is thereunto called, that he may inherit a bleſſing,</hi> 1 Pet: 3.9. For ſo did our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, he left us an example behind him, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, <hi>who, when he was reviled, reviled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when he ſuffered, he threatned not, but committed himſelf to him that judgeth righteouſly,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.21, 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Contrary to this Moderation, is turbulency in actions, and that is, briefly, when men, 1: will be ſtepping beyond the bounds of their lawfull Callings, invading the Magiſtracy or Miniſtry, and attempting to reform abuſes and corruptions in Church and State, when they have no lawful call to it.<note n="(n)" place="margin">In his coal from the Altar, p. <hi>244.</hi>
               </note> Mr: <hi>Ward</hi> wittily calls theſe men, <hi>Fires that cannot keep themſelves
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37143:19"/>
within their own hearths, Spirits that cannot keep themſelves within their own Circles.</hi> Such as theſe, if ye obſerve them, ſhall have many corruptions in their own Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies unreformed, which lie within the Compaſſe of their duty and ability to reform; and yet they, who have not the skill or will to reform abuſes in their own families, will be very hot in talking of reforming the Church, and amending things amiſſe in the State. So ye never knew any men, that would be preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adventuring upon things, for which they have no command, but they did groſly neglect other things moſt manifeſtly commanded. Such men as theſe, are of moſt troubled and troubling Spirits; and I know not, whether they trouble others or themſelves more: Sure it is, they do trouble others, and they do alſo trouble themſelves, but with little thanks from others. But what is the reaſon, that many among us ſhould thus run out and forget themſelves? <q>Surely they think, that if they ſhould not cenſure others, and find fault with ſomething (ſaith<note n="(o)" place="margin">In his E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on <hi>Rom. 12.3.</hi>
                  </note> Mr: <hi>Parre</hi>) they ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted no body, and to be blind, and to have little profited in knowledge, when rather this practice ſhews them to be blind or ill-ſighted: for if they did ſee well and perfectly, they would ſee reaſon to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to judge charitably of the State, in which they live, and to keep themſelves in their own Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. When an old man takes a book to read, he holds it far from him; I take it, not for the ſtrength and goodneſſe of his ſight, but for the weakneſſe and dimneſſe: So when our Schiſmatical and contentious Spirits ſee ſo well afar off, and ſo ill near at hand, it argues them to be dull and thick-ſighted. When <hi>Peter</hi> enquired of Chriſt, <hi>What John ſhould do? What is that to thee?</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>follow thou me,</hi> Joh. 21.21, 22. If things be thus and thus ordered in the Commonwealth and Church by the wiſdom of thy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, whats that to thee? follow thou Chriſt, by walking conſcionably in thine own calling: <hi>Tantumne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37143:20"/>
abs re tuâ otii eſt tibi, aliena ut cures?</hi> wanteſt thou work at home, that thou art ſo buſie abroad? <hi>ſtudy to be quiet, medling with thine own buſineſs,</hi> as the Lord commandeth thee, 1 <hi>Theſſ:</hi> 4.11.</q> 2ly, As he is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulent who goeth beyond his calling: ſo he that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries himſelf turbulently in his calling, oppoſing govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether in Church or State, ſetled by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſowing diviſions, and thereby labouring, as <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Theudas,</hi> to draw away much people after him, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.36, 37. The moderate man meddles little with Civil Government. Suppoſe it be uſurped, let them look to it that are the Uſurpers; if he can but lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſty,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2.</note> he is thankfull to God, and obedient to man. It is not a kingdom, or any ſuch thing that he ſtrives for, but only the kingdom of Heaven, and this he ſteals from the world, whilſt they are all buſie, and in an hurly-burly about the kingdoms, and government and greatneſſe of this world. He loves not to make parties, and draw away people after him; his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal care is, to draw his familie, and then his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, by a godly life and Chriſtian exhortations, and as many as he can by this means, unto heaven. In a word, the moderate man is not ambitious, and therefore not turbulent, he had rather enjoy the Goſpel with qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, than enjoy a Kingdom with tumult. He paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſilently through the world, without making any noiſe, or being pointed at with the finger, as he goes along the ſtreets; and if little, that is notable, be ſaid of him; he is ſure, that there is nothing notorious done by him. So I have diſpatched the firſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and ſhewed you, as exactly as I could, what this Moderation is, both in the Judgement, Affections, and Converſation. I haſten to the ſecond thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Why we are to expreſs Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note>Why it is the duty of a Chriſtian to expreſs Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 1. Becauſe Chriſtian Religion doth enjoyn, and not only ſo (but where it is in truth and in power) doth <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> alſo enable us to carrie our ſelves moderately. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:37143:20"/>
ſerves religion, but to guide and govern our affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Actions? Therefore we are ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, as we can rule our ſelves, the reſt is but form and ſpeculation. <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and brideleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans religion is vain,</hi> James 1.26. It is but a vain religion and unprofitable, that doth not at once both teach a man, and enable him to rule his tongue, to bridle his paſſion, and to keep himſelf within com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. Doth the doctrine of Chriſtianity, which is a doctrine of the Croſs and Self-denial, teach men to be immoderate?</p>
            <p n="2">2. As Chriſtian Religion enjoyneth Moderation, ſo <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Moderation is an honour to our Religion, and <hi>puts to ſhame ſuch as ſpeak evil of us, and falſly accuſe us,</hi> 1 Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: 3.16. Moderation puts a luſtre upon all graces, and therefore is well called by Biſhop <hi>Hall,</hi> the ſilken ſtring running thorough the pearl-chain of all vertues. What were Anger without Moderation, but madneſs? What were Zeal without this, but a furie? as the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſpheres of the heaven would ſoon ſet the whole world on fire, if they ſhould not be ſtaid by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary courſe of the higheſt ſphere in the firmament: ſo the inferiour affections of the mind, if not regulated by a moderate judgement, and the mild motions of the Spirit of God, will ſoon over-heat and over-throw all that a man goes about. The Poets ſhadowed out this, in <hi>Minervaes</hi> golden bridle, wherewith ſhe managed her winged <hi>Pegaſus.</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Tolle hanc &amp; virtus viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um erit, ipſa<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> affectio natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis in perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem magis convertetur, exterminium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> naturae. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſuper <hi>Cant.</hi> Serm. <hi>49.</hi> Et fervor d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretionem eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, &amp; diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio fervorem dirigat.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> calls Diſcretion or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, <hi>Moderatrix &amp; auriga virtutum:</hi> and take away this (ſaith he) and vertue will become vice, and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral affection it ſelf will turn into perturbation, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verwhelm nature. And therefore ſaith one, (quoting <hi>Bernard,</hi> but I cannot find the place) as zeal muſt erect our diſcretion, that we be not too ſlow: ſo diſcretion muſt direct our zeal, that we be not over-haſty.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That known and generally received Maxim, which <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> is the ſubſtance of the Law and the Prophets, <hi>Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:37143:21"/>
ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them,</hi> Mat. 7.12. doth ſtrongly engage us unto Moderation. For we would have others moderate to us, why ſhould not we then be moderate to others? <hi>David</hi> hit himſelf a foul blow, when he was ſo angry againſt the rich man, that had violently taken away the poor mans lamb, and reſolved, that he ſhould die; not conſidering what he had done to <hi>Uriah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.5. How ſparing men are of themſelves, and how ſparing would they have their Brethren to be towards them, and yet how rigid they are to others? Some, ſaith<note n="(q)" place="margin">Alii tam vehementer contra aliorum delicta zelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut videri poſſent eſurire &amp; ſitire juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, ſi eſſet apud eos de ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is quoque pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catis idem ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium; ſed nunc pondus &amp; pondus utrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> abominatio apud deum. Nam contra a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios tam impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denter, quàm inutiliter aeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant; ſeipſos tam incipien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, quam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utiliter pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant. <hi>Bern.</hi> de advent. Dom. ſermon. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> are ſo zealous againſt the faults of others, as if they did hunger and thirſt after ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; which were very commendable, if they were likewiſe as zealous againſt their own Sins, but ſaith he, <hi>Pondus &amp; pondus,</hi> divers weights are an abomination to the Lord; and they who do ſo impudently and vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſure others, do as fooliſhly and unprofitably flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The good of others and the peace of the Church do ſtrongly engage us unto moderation; <hi>Si virtutum fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ille ſit maximus, qui plurimorum ſpectat profectum, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio propè omnium pulcherima eſt;</hi> Ambroſ. <hi>de paenitent. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>adv. Novat. ca.</hi> 1. If that be the chief end of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (ſaith he) to reſpect the profit of many, Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moderation is the moſt excellent. The anſwer of <hi>Apollonius</hi> to <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> was full of excellent inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> asked him what was <hi>Neroes</hi> overthrow, he anſwered, <hi>Nero</hi> could tune and touch the Harp well, but in Government, ſometimes he uſed to wind the Pipes too high, ſometimes to let them down too low; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>4</label> And certain it is, that nothing deſtroys authority ſo much, as the unequal and untimely interchange of Power preſſed too far, and relaxed too much. And if it be asked, what hath been the ruine of our Church (lately one of the famous Churches in the World) what, but becauſe with <hi>Nero</hi> we could never yet hit of the Golden Mean, but have either been too high or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37143:21"/>
too low. When I conſider into what a diſtracted eſtate our Church is brought through our mutual and immoderate contentions, I cannot but think of the Prophets earthen Bottels daſhed one againſt another, <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.12, 13, 14. and of <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of <hi>Burgundie</hi> his Embleme, Flint and Steel beaten one againſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till both be waſted, affording no other iſſue but Fire. Between our Yea, and your Nay ſaid<note n="(r)" place="margin">Inter licet noſtrum, &amp; non licet veſtrum, mutant &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migant animae Chriſtianorum. <hi>Optat.</hi> adv. Parmen. Mr. <hi>Ward</hi> in his coal from the Altar. p. <hi>254.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Opta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus</hi> to the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> the Souls of Chriſtians waver and are unſetled. And have not we brought it to the ſame paſs by our immoderate quarrels among our ſelves, that many a Chriſtians ſoul ſtaggers and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſolved, others leap aſide into the Tents of Popery and multitudes perverted and become they know not what themſelves. <q>We have made the Devill but too much ſport already, who hath thrown in Bones to ſet us together by the ears, whilſt he lets in the common Enemy upon us. Moderation and Charity are the Builders of Churches; ſtrife about Trifles hath waſted many famous ones, and placed the Temples of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> where the Golden Candleſtick was wont to ſtand. We pity the former ages, contending about levened and unlevened bread, keeping of <hi>Easter,</hi> faſting on <hi>Sundays,</hi> &amp;c. the future ages will do the like for us. Oh that the Lord would put into the hearrs both of Governors and parties to theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, once to make an end of theſe <hi>Midiniatiſh</hi> wars; that we might jointly pour out the vials of our zeal upon the Throne of the Beaſt.</q> God knows, the Church hath not loſt, but the Adverſaries of it have gotten as much by our immoderate Domeſtical diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; a forein Enemy cannot wiſh us a greater miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, or themſelves a greater advantage, than this. This makes the <hi>Turks</hi> pray to God to keep the Chriſtians a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> variance, and encouraged one of their Emperors to ſay, when his Council diſwaded him from a war againſt the <hi>Germans</hi> by reaſon of their multitude, that he feared them not, becauſe ſooner would his fingers be all of one length, than their Princes be all of one mind. As
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:37143:22"/>
more grievous, and leſs eaſie to be borne; for if we mingle ſin with our ſufferings, it is, as if a man ſhould put poyſon into ſome wholſom phyſick; beſides, it is by patience, that we poſſeſs our ſouls in all ſufferings, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. and if through immoderation and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we ſhall be dipo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeſt of our Souls in a time of ſuffering, what a ſad condition are we in then?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Uſe of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note>The uſe of all that hath been ſaid, ſhall be to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort us unto Moderation, a grace ſo excellent, and yet ſo much out of Grace with the times. I know indeed, that moderate men are commonly cruſhed between the extreme parties on both ſides, and in this world (ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally) they get the leaſt preferment; it faring with them as with the gueſt that ſat in the midſt of the Table, who could reach to neither Meſſe, above him, nor beneath him. But to overballance theſe temporal inconveniencies of Moderation, I ſhall offer unto the Readers thoughts the benefits of Moderation, as I find them to my hand, in an author eminent for learning and Moderation.<note place="margin">The benefits of Moderation.</note> And</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> A ſound judgment.</note>1. A well-informed judgement is of it ſelf a great preferment; which a man that wants Moderation ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath: for they that have ſo much heat, uſually have but little light, or elſe their light is no better than darkneſs, the miſt of their paſſions dims their eyes, that they cannot ſee clearly. Now what is of more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue next to truth, than a judgement well informed with truth? Certainly (ſaith the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi>) it is Heaven upon Earth, to have a mans mind move in charity, reſt in providence, and turn upon the poles of truth; all which a moderate Chriſtian hath. It is the greateſt folly in the world, for any man in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, to entertain a lie, or to poſſeſſe himſelf of falſhood; and therefore it requires the greateſt care of a Chriſtian, that in Religion he be not found to receive any thing, which is not ſound and grounded upon truth. It is royal and noble liberty to be under the command of truth, and the more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37143:22"/>
ſubject a man is to truth, the more free, noble and raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he is: and of choice a man ſhould deliver himſelf up abſolutely, without any reſervation to truth; it is a mans height and excellency thus to do. But it is a mans greateſt debaſement to enſlave his conſcience to an error; there is not a greater ſlave among the Turks than he that doth charge his conſcience with a falſhood. For, for any man to lay ſtreſs, where God hath laid none, or more than God hath, is to be ſuperſtitious; and Superſtition is ſomething worſe than nothing, the more it grows in being, it is worſe than if it had no being, for it is a lye. A ſuperſtitious man ſeems to ſerve God, when either he doth not ſerve him at all, or elſe according to his own fancy, &amp; to obſerve God ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitiouſly is worſe, in ſome ſort, than to neglect God, for it doth abuſe him. That which a man takes for truth in Religion, he ſubmits himſelf to it, lets it have dominion over his conſcience, frames his converſation ſo, that all his actions may conſiſt with it: and if a man entertain an error or a falſhood in this manner, doth he not then part with al his liberty, doth he not make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the worſt ſlave in the world? and as it is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt cruelty to die by a mans own hand; ſo it is the baſeſt ſlavery for a man to ſubmit himſelf to an error of his own forging. And again, it is the greateſt wrong to God; for this is the utmoſt capacity of a creature, for a creature to entertain this Maxime ſo, as to ſay, I will ſubmit my ſelf and all my deſigns, and my will, will I ſubmit to it, and live by it; I ſay, thus for a man to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an error, is the greateſt wrong to God, that can be; for no more can be given to God, and ſo much is to be given to none but God and his truth. And ſhall a man ſerve an error thus? it is much better to be no body, than to be ſomebody thus. That man is not true to his own eaſe, who chargeth himſelf with any thing, whereof he hath not aſſurance. We ſhould never ſtand deeply charged with any thing but truth, falſhood is a barren thing, and affords no ſtrength or comfort to him, that ſuffers for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:37143:23"/>This is very neceſſary to awaken men, for we are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry careleſſe about right information; all, but moderate men, take things upon truſt, and pin their faith to this or that mans ſleeve. Wee muſt not build any other thing than the foundation will bear, if we would have it abide a fierie trial by God or men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. Good mens fancies, opinions and conceits, built upon Gods foundations will not endure Gods fire. We ſhould lay no more ſtreſſe upon any thing,<note place="margin">Superſtitio, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra quod Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutum.</note> than either Scripture or reaſon hath put upon it. Religion hath two very bad neighbours in the world, on the one ſide profaneneſs, on the other ſuperſtition (for ſo I chuſe to call it according to the notion of the word, though men think otherwiſe) profaneneſs denies religion altogether, takes no notice of God in the world; ſuperſtition adulrerates religion: prophaneneſs ſtrives to looſe man from God, by cutting him off from God altogether; and the ſuperſtitious man thinks to bind men to God with things of his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing, in doctrine, worſhip, or diſcipline. This is that therefore, which Divines call Self-denial, as to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, when we deliver up our minds as a fair ſheet of paper, to be enſtamped upon, and written with the finger of God alone. Any one that ſteps out of the way, out of affectation or affection to a party, is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in this part of Self-denial. Therefore ſuperſtition is a piece of folly under a fair appearance of wiſdom. The ſuperſtitious man thinks he obſerves God, but his obſervance is a neglect, yea an abuſe of God; he thinks he hath made ſure of God, when he hath bound him only, as <hi>Delilah</hi> did <hi>Sampſon,</hi> with cords, which will break, becauſe God never ſubmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted to them; he imagines ſuch and ſuch a thing, but it is all nothing. We ſhould have a care of error therefore; for a man may be ſuperſtitious in the ſeeming good uſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yea where he ſeems to be moſt for God, if he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a place of Scripture beyond its ſenſe, or if he graft notions upon a Scripture, which neither that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture nor another place will bear, he is ſuperſtitious; he is not an Interpreter of the Scripture, but makes new
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37143:23"/>
Scripture; yea, though thoſe notions pretend to holineſs, and have the zeal of holineſs written on their foreheads: this very thing is to lie for God, it is but <hi>pia fraus,</hi> an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceit, and ſo much the worſe, becauſe it carries with it ſuch a pretence; and it were better that any truth of God were expoſed to hazard, than that we ſhould come in with a lie to maintain it, for by thus doing a man ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelf the Maſter of truth, and not a Subject to it.</p>
            <p>Now this benefit hath a moderate man, for the moſt part above others, a well informed judgement; For he takes more deliberation to conſider of things, than haſtie and hot ſpirits do; and whilſt the two Adverſe parties are wrangling and ſcuffing about the queſtion, he ſtands by, and gets the truth from them both; and by his carefull ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of them, better than they in their heat can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve themſelves, he is able to convince them both of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, if they be but willing to refer their Controverſie to Arbitration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A quiet mind is another advantage of Moderation.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> A quiet mind.</note> He that is immoderate is far from this inward tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for he is alwayes in an hurrie, and his immoderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ariſeth from the weakneſs of judgement, and the ſtrength of violent and inordinate paſſions in him: and how can ſuch an one enjoy true quiet of mind? eſpecially if you think upon that of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which is moſt true, That God hath ſo ordained it, that every inordinate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſhould be a puniſhment to it ſelf. Any one but a moderate perſon, ſeeks for quiet of mind by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, and not by ſubduing his paſſions and affections, which when he hath done, his paſſions grow more by yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and he becomes a ſlave to the foreſt Tyrant. If a man yield to his paſſion, is he any more quiet? is he not much more troubled and diſtracted? is he not himſelf the inſtrument of his own vexation, and ſuffers more violence in his own ſpirit, than he offers to another? If a mans Covetouſneſs or Ambition hath made him immoderate, and by the ſale of his diſtempered zeal, he hath purchaſed to himſelf great revenues and promotions in Church or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37143:24"/>
State, do ye think that this man is now at quiet, doth he not yet thirſt after more, or elſe his wounded conſcience bleeds within him, and refuſeth to take any content in what he hath? true inward peace ariſeth from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the judgement to the word of God, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of the affections to ſuch a judgement. And if ſo, I will be bold to affirm, that inward peace is the ſole privilege and prerogative royal of a moderate mind, that hath learned how to rule its ſelf. The immoderate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon through the continnal mutinies of his paſſions, cannot but be ſubject to perpetual unquietneſs, and like the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſea caſting out mire and dirt.</p>
            <p>And that which addes to the inward quiet of a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſon,<note place="margin">Mr. Fuller.</note> is his outward ſecuritie, <q>for as his temporal hopes are not great, ſo his fears are the leſſe. He fears not to have the ſplinters of his party, when it breaks, flie into his eyes, or to be buried under the ruines of his ſide, if ſuppreſt; that diſgrace, which doth uſually attend the conquered partie in this kind, never troubles him.</q> Thus, if he have not much Credit in the world, yet he hath much ſecuritie in himſelf, which is far better; for if he have no hopes to riſe, he hath no fears to fall. Yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> A Conſcience clear from Schiſm.</note>3. A moderate mans conſcience is clear from raiſing Schiſms in the Church, and ſo is not in danger of that woe of our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.2, 3. <hi>Woe to him, by whom offences come, it were better that a milstone were hanged about his neck and he caſt into the ſea.</hi> And in this he hath more comfort, than they that riſe in this manner have credit. Woe to thoſe Miniſters that make unneceſſary diviſions and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties among the people, that they may get themſelves a name, and be cryed up by many followers. Certainly ſome men have a ſad account to give to God for the Rents which have been made in the Church. And if any godly men have had an hand in them, I profeſs, I do even trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think, what a ſharp Conflict they ſhall have with themſelves, when they come to die, and caſt their eye back upon the Church, which they have (though not intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally) miſerably rent, and is not now in their power to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37143:24"/>
heal; they ſhall be ſaved, but <hi>vix, agrè duriter,</hi> hardly, even as by fire, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. And for other men, <hi>Oſtendant quod volunt de Religione &amp; fide digladiantes Theologi, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith one, Let your Swaſhbucklers or Fencing-Divines pretend what they will for Faith and Religion, they love neither Peace nor Truth truly, if they do not love both. If we would have the waters of piety and verity to be clear, the way is not to ſtir them and trouble them, but to let them ſettle in peace, and run down in practice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Conſtancy in Religion.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <q>The Moderate man is a great deal more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and durable in his Religion, whilſt violent men reel from one extremity to another.<note place="margin">Mr. Fuller.</note> For being here in his way to Heaven, and jogging on a good Travellers pace, he over-takes and out-goes many vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men, whoſe hot and ill-grounded zeal, was quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tired.</q> The Moderate man is alwaies going on in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Journey towards Heaven, whereas the other tumbles up and down, but rids no way.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Laſtly, once in an Age it goes very hard,<note place="margin">Univerſal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation in the Concluſion</note> if the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate man be not in faſhion, each extreme courts him to make them friends; and ſurely he hath a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to be Peace-maker between two oppoſite parties. Time-ſervers are ofttimes left in the lurch, if they do not only give their word for the times in their conſtant diſcourſe, but alſo give their Bond for them, and write in their defence: ſuch when the times turn afterwards to another extream, are left in the briars, and as Mr. <hi>Fuller</hi> ſaith wittily, come off very hardly from the Bill of their own hands. And therefore that Council, which he gives is (as every thing elſe, that he hath written) moſt excellent. He that intends to meet with one in a great Fair, and knows not where, may ſooner find him by ſtanding ſtill in ſome principal place there, than by traverſing it up and down: ſo take thy Stand upon ſome good ground in Religion, and keep thy Station in a moderate, yet fixed poſture, never turning after the times to follow them, and an hundred to one, they will come to thee once in thy life time, and be as glad to meet with thee, as thou wouldſt be to meet with them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Unto theſe inducements to Moderation, I will adde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37143:25"/>
only ſome directions,<note place="margin">Directions to make the word of God our Rule.</note> and that is this, If ye will be Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, make the written word of God your Rule, for the written word is uniform and invariable, and ſo will he be (ſo far as humane frailty will permit) that makes the word his Rule; he that keeps cloſe to the word will be uniform and alwaies like to himſelf; not <hi>Proteus</hi> like, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appearing in a new ſhape. The word of God will ballance and ſettle the Judgment, and teach a man to get the Maſtery over his own affections. The word is called a Line,<note place="margin">In Com. loc. de S. Scriptur.</note> 
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.5. The <hi>Hehrew</hi> word (as ſaith <hi>Gerrard</hi>) doth ſignifie the Tongue of a Ballance, <hi>Juxta quam aequili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brium conſtituitur,</hi> that makes the Scales even &amp; equal. As we deſire Moderation therfore, &amp; to be exact in it (becauſe the more exact it is, the nearer it commeth to an exact <hi>ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilibrium</hi>) ſtudy to know the word in its own ſenſe, then ſubmit to it, and make it your rule. For the improvement of this direction, obſerve the following particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Make the Word your rule, not the Times. A man cannot be truly moderate and a Time-ſerver;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Not the Times.</note> the times change ſo frequently, ſo ſuddenly, and ſometimes ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently from one extreme to another. The times under <hi>Diocleſian</hi> were <hi>Pagan;</hi> under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> Chriſtian; under <hi>Constantius</hi> Arrian, under <hi>Julian Apoſtate;</hi> and under <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian</hi> Chriſtian again; and all within the Age of one man, the Term of ſeaventy years (as ſaith my Author) Could he have been a moderate man, that ſhould have been alwaies of the Religion for the time being? Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hiſtory gives us an example of ſuch an one, <hi>viz.</hi> A Biſhop of our own Nation, Dr. <hi>Kitchin,</hi> who for Covetouſneſs could diſſemble all Religions with the times, ſo as to be the Popes ſworn Servant, while he was an Abbot; an half Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, when King <hi>Henry</hi> had caſt off the Pope; A Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant under King <hi>Henry the</hi> ſixth; a down-right Papiſt with Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> a Parliament Proteſtant again, when he took the oath of Supremacie under Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Was this a moderate man? No, but <hi>Cambden</hi> calls him rightly, the Calamity of his See: And ſuch unſound and unſetled men are the Calamity of this age. Dr. <hi>Playfere</hi> in a Sermon entituled <hi>The Path-way to Perſecution,</hi> having his Text out of <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. I preſſe forward towards the mark; ſaith,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:37143:25"/>
               <q>that Temporizers run beſides the mark by going about in a Circle; they go about many things but bring about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; they do <hi>omnia pro tempore, nihil pro veritate,</hi> all things for the Times, nothing for the Truth; they make a period, but never a full ſtop; they are alwaies learning, but never come to the knowledge of the Truth.</q> The Times are inconſtant and variable; How can that mans carriage then be equable and uniform, who maketh them his Rule to walk by, and not the Word? Religion hath two great Enemies, Superſtition and Innovation; he that would not be an old Time-ſerver, or a new Time-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, muſt walk between theſe two, if he would make ſtreight paths unto himſelf, and his Guide muſt be the Word. <hi>My Son</hi> (ſaith the wiſe man) <hi>fear thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change, Prov.</hi> 24.21. Then we muſt meddle little with the times; for what is more given to change than they? the Scripture bids us inſtead of ſerving the times, to ſave our ſelves from them, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.40. to beware of them, <hi>See that ye walk not as fools, but as wiſe, becauſe the daies are evill,</hi> Epheſians 5.16, 17. And then the Apoſtle addes immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Wherefore be not unwiſe, but underſtanding what the Will of the Lord is.</hi> We muſt labour therefore ye ſee (eſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally in evill times) to know what the will of God is, out of the VVord, that we may follow what is pleaſing unto him, not that which is pleaſing unto the times: otherwiſe we are not wiſe; for the greateſt wiſdome is to comply with God, as I think, and not with the times. The times that we live in, are evill and perilous times; he that ſhall bind himſelf Apprentiſe to ſerve them 7 year, ſhal find it very difficult to ſerve them, ſo as always to pleaſe the times; and impoſſible always to ſerve them, &amp; pleaſe God, and remain <hi>idem homo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Make the VVord you rule, not divine Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. VVe may make dangerous conſtructions of providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if we reſt in them, &amp; do not compare theſe Revelations of God in his works, with, and interpret them by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation that he hath made in his word. When <hi>David</hi> had ſpent ſome time and ſerious thoughts upon the ſtudy of that great point touching the outward viſible proſperity of wicked men, and the outward ſeeming infelicity of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37143:26"/>
godly, he profeſſeth, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 13.16, 17. when I thought to know this it was too painful for me, until I went into the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary of God, then underſtood I their end. It was evident from the event, that it was the will of God, the Iſraelites ſhould be worſted in that war, which they upon juſt grounds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook againſt the <hi>Benjamites, Jud.</hi> 20. but if any ſhould from hence have concluded, that the Iſraelites quarrel was not good, becauſe their ſucceſs was bad, he would have made a dangerous miſ-conſtruction of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in that particular caſe. Therefore we muſt always make ſuch a conſtruction of the various works of Gods providence, as may conſiſt with the verity of the ſtanding and invariable rule of his word: otherwiſe we ſhall loſe, and incautelouſly engage our ſelves to juſtifie any unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable opinion or practice, which God in his juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and for ends at preſent unknown to us, permits to ſpread and proſper, when he doth nothing leſs than approve of them to be true and juſt. <hi>The judgements of the Lord are unſearchable, and his ways paſt finding out,</hi> Rom. 11.33. We muſt not think therefore to trace him here. If we can parallel any paſſage of providence with the like inſtance out of Scripture, then we may probably conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture what the mind of God is in it; and what diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of heart, and frame of life the Lord doth expect from us; otherwiſe we cannot; nor are we to faſhion our lives &amp; hearts according to the providence of God, but according to his word, which teacheth us rightly to interpret pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. For providence (generally) is a Revelation of what God had, unknown to us, decreed from eternity that he would do, not a revelation of what he would have us do; unleſs we know the mind of God in that Providence; which if we cannot gather from the Word, our own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are but incompetent Judges, and long enough may we conjecture ere we make a right concluſion. How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrange, and almoſt not to be paralleld occurrences of Divine Providence have we in this Nation, within a few years met withall? if any one now ſhould have ſteer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his courſe not according to the Compaſs of the Word, but every preſent and ſudden apparition of Providence, I doe not ſee how he could keep a ſtreight path; but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:37143:26"/>
he muſt walk in crooked and by-ways, and ways not caſt up; or elſe <hi>in Circulo,</hi> and ſo for diverſe years have rid no ground in his journey toward the heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Make the Word your rule,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of men.</note> not the judgement or practice of any man, be he never ſo learned and godly, further than ye ſee them to be agreeable unto the Word. Chriſts example we muſt follow, for he left us an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>that we ſhould follow his ſteps,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. But we may not write after any other Copy farther than we ſee it to agree with the original. <hi>Be ye followers of me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) as I alſo am of Christ,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.1. So far as we ſee any man to follow Chriſt, we may follow him, but no farther. I preſume none of you will ſay, that we are bound to follow <hi>Peter,</hi> though a Diſciple and Apoſtle of Chriſt, in denying his Maſter. The beſt men have had their errors and their failings, which we have therefore recorded, to teach us that we ſhould make the examp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of no man, how godly ſoever, our rule to walk by: for there is not the beſt man living, but may and doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tread awry; and I am perſwaded, the Lord ſuffers men of great parts many times to fall into errors of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and men of much grace to fall fouly in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, leſt others might have their perſons in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, if not adoration. Were I a man of the greateſt learning, and holineſs of Converſation in the world, I think, I ſhould as earneſtly pray to God, that others might not truſt to me, as that I might not truſt to my ſelf; for when I once ſaw people begin to applaud me, and imitate me, <hi>ex induſtria,</hi> I ſhould then be very fearfull that the Lord would leave me to my ſelf, as he often doth the moſt able and Godly men, that people may ſee they are men of like paſſions &amp; infirmities with themſelves. The Pſalmiſt, (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>) compares the Law of God to a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.105. Good example bears it. It is ſafe following him, that carries the lighr; but if he walk without the light, he ſhall walk without me. For that a man ſhould be ſo wedded to any mans perſon, that he muſt make no ſeparation from his infirmities, is both ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdly ſervile and unchriſtian.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37143:27"/>And that for which I do the rather urge this ſo much is, becauſe I ſee in theſe times, wherein godly men are of ſuch different opinions, many religious perſons judge themſelves moſt ſecure from falling, by leaning unto the examples of ſome eminently learned and Godly Miniſters: but the ſafeſt way is to have recourſe to the word; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine by ſound reaſons, and plain teſtimonies deduced from thence, whether their opinions or practices be good; and if ye find that the Scripture approves of them, then make uſe of their example for imitation and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement. As a man in a ſhip hath his hand upon the rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and his eye upon the Star: ſo it is good to have your eye upon the examples of godly and judicious men; but let your hand be alwaies upon the Scripture, let go your hold of that, &amp; ye will run the hazard of making a ſhipwrack of your faith. I dare confidently ſay, that there is no truly godly man (though never ſo learned) will preſume ſo much upon himſelf, as to impoſe upon others his example or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, farther than he can prove the neceſſity thereof by Scripture; why then ſhould any man take a yoke upon him, which is not laid upon him? I exhort you (ſaith <note n="(t)" place="margin">Vos horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ut non quod vobis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, aut nobis, audire quaera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis; ſed quod domino com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placet &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonum eſt Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturis, <hi>Baſil.</hi> in Hom. adv. <hi>Sabellian.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baſil</hi>) not ſo much to enquire what pleaſeth you, and what pleaſeth me, but what is pleaſing to God, and agreeable to the Scriptures. To what incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had bound himſelf, if he had ſtrictly tied himſelf to the Fathers before him (though very holy and of great learning) is well enough known. But <note n="(u)" place="margin">Alios Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptores praeter Canonicos ita lego, ut quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâlibet ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, doctrinâve perpolleant, non ideo verum pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quia ipſi ita ſenſerunt, ſed quia mihi vel per alios auctores Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicos, vel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babili ratione, quòd à verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te non abhorre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, perſuadere potuerint. <hi>Aug.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>19.</hi> ad <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> ſaith he) other Writers, beſides thoſe that are Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, I ſo read, that however they may excel in learning and pietie, yet I do not think any thing to be true, meerly becauſe they have thought ſo, unles they can perſwade me by certain teſtimonies of the Scripture, or probable rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that what they ſay is true. But was <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that other men after him ſhould deal with his Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as he did with the Fathers before him? Yes, For <note n="(x)" place="margin">Negare non poſſum, nec de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, ſicut in ipſis majoribus, ita multa eſſe in tam multis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puſculis meis, quae poſſunt iuſto judicio ac nullâ temeritate culpari. <hi>Aug.</hi> ad <hi>Vincent. Victor.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> (ſaith he) I neither can nor ought to deny, but as in the Antients, ſo likewiſe in my works there are many things which may juſtly and without any raſhneſs be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37143:27"/>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">Neminem velim ſic am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plecti omnia mea, ut me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatur, niſi in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is, in quibus me non errata perspexerint. Nam propter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae nunc facio li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bros Retractio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ut nec meipſum in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus me ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſuiſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrem. <hi>Aug,</hi> lib. de Bon. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverantiae, cap. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> And I would not have any man ſo to embrace all my writings, as to follow me in all things, unleſſe he ſee that I have not erred in them; for therefore do I make my book of Retractations, to ſhew that I my ſelf have not in all things followed my ſelf. Above all,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Take heed of making crooked the rule, and wreſting it to the maintenance of any ertoneous or ſelf-Conceit. This is a dreadfull ſin, and he who doth it knowingly, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth lies in hypocriſie. It was a fearfull evil for <hi>Lucifer</hi> to ſay, I will aſcend up and be like the higheſt; is it not as great a ſin for any to ſeek to make the higheſt become like <hi>Lucifer?</hi> ſo do they, that drag down the Scriptures to patronize any erroneous opinion of their own heads, or any evil of their own hearts; they go about to make the bleſſed God, and the Holy Ghoſt the Father of lies, than which, what can be more abominable? It is accounted a capital crime in a Commonwealth to put the States ſtamp upon falſe Coin; and to put the ſtamp of the Spirit of God upon an error, upon a conceit of a mans own, is certainly a great evil before the Lord. We doe with one conſent blame the Papiſts, for making the Scriptures a noſe of wax, that a man may writhe which way he pleaſeth; let not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proteſtant practiſe that, which he ſo ſeverely condemns in a Papiſt, be his pretence never ſo plauſible. Yet alas, who doth not ſee, and cannot but be grieved to ſee how horribly we wreſt the Scriptures? I ſhould not have ſaid it, but that it is too manifeſt to be hid. For it is but uſual, when mens opinions do not agree with the Scriptures, to wreſt the Scriptures to make them agree with their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. The reaſon of it is this, Men receive opinions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have well examined them by the Scripture; &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once entertained them out of weakneſs, the ſtrength of their pride cauſeth them to uſe this means for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of them; and though it be but ſome additional point in Divinitie, yet now it muſt needs be fundamental in Religion, becauſe it is fundamental to his reputation. <note n="(z)" place="margin">Optimus Scripturae lector est, qui dictoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intelligentiam ex dictis expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat, potius quàm importat et retulerit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis quàm at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulerit, nec co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat id videri dictis contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, quod ante lectionem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpſerit intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligendum. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> De Trin.</note> 
               <hi>Hilarie</hi> hath an excellent ſaying, with which I will ſhut up this head. He is the beſt reader of the Scripture (ſaith he) that carrieth away the ſenſe of any place of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:37143:28"/>
Scripture, after he hath read it, not he that bringeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with him, and ſo even after a forcible manner, labours to make that appear to be in ſuch a Scripture, which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed was to be found there before he came to read it. Men that do thus, may not unfitly be compared to Camels, that diink not of the fountain (as Hiſtorians tell us) till they have pudled in them with their feet.</p>
            <p>But what if the Scripture in ſome things be ſilent, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing only rules in the general, as that 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> (not peremptorily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining any thing in particular to be obſerved in ſuch a Church) what is moſt convenient for a moderate man to do in ſuch a caſe? To this I anſwer, according to mine own judgement.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, That it is moſt meet, where the Scripture is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, we ſhould hearken to the voice of the Church; in the firſt place the Primitive Church, and next to that, the Church wherein we live. Where the Scripture ſpeaks, I would have the Church only our Comment; but where the Scripture is ſilent, I would have the Church our Text, and judge it moſt fitting that men ſhould follow the great Wheel of the Church, and move by that, not reſerving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proper poles or motions from the Epycicles of their own brains. It argues monſtrous pride in any man, in things of indifferency (for in things of abſolute neceſſity, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Scripture is reſolute) to lean unto his own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or the opinion of a party, againſt the general aſſent of the Church. I ſee no reaſon, why our own Church ſhould be ſlighted by them, that cannot deny themſelves to be her children; much leſs the Primitive and Ancient Church from the Apoſtles times. Where the Scripture is ſilent, let us hearken and adhere to her teſtimony. I knew that Novelty hath much prevailed againſt Antiquity in this laſt age, but I ſee little hopes of Moderation, till An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity come into more eſtimation, than at preſent it is. In the mean time, (for ſo I chuſe to break off abruptly) Conſider what hath been ſpoken, and the Lord give you underſtanding and Moderation in all things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37143:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
